<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The temporysour (that is to saye: the obseruer of tyme, or he that chaungeth with the tyme.) Compyled in Latyn by the excellent clarke Wolfangus Musculus, and tra[n]slated into Frenche by M. Vallerain Pullain. And out of Frenche into Inglishe by R.P. 1555.</title>
            <author>Musculus, Wolfgang, 1497-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840258</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840258</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 855:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The temporysour (that is to saye: the obseruer of tyme, or he that chaungeth with the tyme.) Compyled in Latyn by the excellent clarke Wolfangus Musculus, and tra[n]slated into Frenche by M. Vallerain Pullain. And out of Frenche into Inglishe by R.P. 1555.</title>
                  <author>Musculus, Wolfgang, 1497-1563.</author>
                  <author>Poullain, Valérand, d. 1559 or 60.</author>
                  <author>Pownall, Robert, 1520-1571.</author>
                  <author>Curione, Celio Secondo, 1503-1569. Excellent admonicion and resolution, of the godlye and famous learned man Celius secundus Curio. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[126] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by H. Singleton?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1555. In the month of July. [1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.P. = R. Pownall.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes: An excellent admonicion and resolution, of the godlye and famous learned man Celius secundus Curio, from a letter in an unidentified work of Celio Secundus Curione.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:1"/>
            <p>¶The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poryſour
(that is to ſaye: the obſeruer of tyme,
or he that chaungeth with the tyme.) Compy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in Latyn by the excellent Clarke Wolfan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus
Muſculus, and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into Frenche
by M. Vallerain Pullain. And out of
Frenche into Ingliſhe by R. P.
1555.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>iij. Regum xviij.</bibl>
               <p>☞How long will ye hault on both ſydes, yf
the Lord be God, folowe him. But if Baal be
he, then go after him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>☞☞<hi>IMPRINTED.</hi>☞☞
Anno Domini. 1555.
In the Moneth of
Iulij.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:2"/>
            <head>❀Grace mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye
and peace from God oure euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge
father in the bloude of Ieſus Chriſt, by
the communication of his holy ſpyryte be mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiplied
vnto the (O Ingland) into the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brafinge
of the trew honour of God in
his word, and the forſakinge of al
Idolatrye and Ypocreſie.</head>
            <p>IN calling to my remembraunce (O In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland)
thou cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trye of my natiuitie, thy
miſerable preſent ſtate, ouerwhelmed
with iniquitie, wherin veritie is exiled,
godlynes ſecluded, vertue defaced, fidelitie
ſuppreſſed, and trueth impriſoned. And on the
other ſyde, Falſhod retayned, lyes imbraſed,
impiete cheriſhed, vyce auaunced, Infidelitie
extolled, and vntrueth ſet at lybertie, wherein
trew relygion is altered into ſuperſticion, the
worde of God into mens traditions, the holy
Sacraments into blaſphemous ſacrifices and
ſuperſticious Ceremonies, and the trew wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
of god into execrable ydolatrie, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in
thy faythful naturall natyf Kyng is chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
into a ſuperſticious vnnaturall forreyne
Prince. Thy worthye Maieſtrates, Nobilitie
and Rulers, into faynt harted tymerous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
ruled of other theyr inferiours. Thy vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelant
Biſhoppes and faythfull Miniſters,
into greuous wolues and bloudthurſtye mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers.
<pb facs="tcp:4739:3"/>
And thy infinite numbre of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
and faythful Chriſtians, into diſſembling
ypocrites, and hollow harted Papiſtes.) I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered
with my ſelfe what mighte be the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doupted
cauſe of this ſo miſerable an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">Pſa. c. vij</note>
for the certaynte whereof I repayred vnto
the worde of God,<note place="margin">Num. 16 ij. eſd. ix.</note> the onelye diſcloſer of all
trueth in doutfull matters: wheras notably I
found,<note place="margin">prou. 28.</note> Sinne, to be the vndoupted cauſe of all
theſe alterations,<note place="margin">Eſa. 3. 13.</note> plagues, and mutacions. For
Sinne was the cauſe of Adams expulſion out<note place="margin">Ier. 5. 30</note>
of Paradyſe,<note place="margin">Ezec. 23.</note> of the ouerflowinge &amp; drowning
of the worlde,<note place="margin">Amo. ix.</note> of the conſuming of Sodome &amp;
Gomor with brunſtone and fyre,<note place="margin">Dani. ix,</note> of the often
captyuitie and ſlaughter of the people of god:<note place="margin">Iudi. 5. 8.</note>
ſometyme by the Egiptians,<note place="margin">Gene. iij.</note> ſometyme by the
Madianites,<note place="margin">Gene. vij</note> Moabites, Amorites, Philiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
Aſſyrians,<note place="margin">Ge. 13. 19</note> Caldians and Babilonians, &amp;
the finall ſubuerſion of Ieruſalem by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes.<note place="margin">Iudi. 3. 4 6. 11. 13. iiij. Reg. xvij. xxv.</note>
Euen ſo is Sinne now the cauſe that
God taketh awaye the light of his word from
vs, and geueth vs ouer to errour &amp; darkenes.
Sinne is the cauſe that he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away our<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note>
vertuous Kinges and Princes,<note place="margin">Lu. 19. 21</note> and in ſtede of
them hath geuen vs ypocrites to raygne ouer<note place="margin">Amos. 8.</note>
vs.<note place="margin">Ioh. xij.</note> Sinne is the cauſe that he hath taken away
the hartes of our Nobilitie,<note place="margin">Iob. 18. xxxviij.</note> Counſayl &amp; Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes
in makinge them fayntharted &amp; weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges,<note place="margin">Iob. 34.</note>
being contented to ſubmit theyr neckes
vnder the yocke of ſtraungers.<note place="margin">Dani. iiij</note> Sinne is the
cauſe that God hath taken away from his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Eſay. iij.</note>
his trew Preachers,<note place="margin">Leui. 26.</note> vertuous Miniſters,
and faythfull Shepeherdes,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> in geuinge them
<pb facs="tcp:4739:3"/>
ouer into the mouthes of moſt cruell wolues,<note place="margin">Iere. iiij.</note>
rauening thefes &amp; fugitiue hyrelinges.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 28</note> Sinne
is the cauſe that God hath ſent a daſinge into<note place="margin">Eſay. lix.</note>
the heartes of his people,<note place="margin">Iob. xij.</note> to beleue lyes, &amp; not
to credyte the truth: but to grope after vanite,<note place="margin">Iere. vij.</note>
thinking by playing the ypocrites,<note place="margin">Eze. xiij.</note> to kepe the
thinge that they ſhall moſte certaynely forgo.<note place="margin">Nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij. ij. Teſſ. ij</note>
Finally to conclude. Sinne is the vndoubted
cauſe (as teſtifieth the ſcriptures) of al plages<note place="margin">Amos. ix</note>
miſfortunes,<note place="margin">Leui. 26.</note> ruynes, mutacions, captiuities,
and deſtructions.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> And vnles thou repente in
tyme (O Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) it wylbe the cauſe of thy fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
deſolation and vtter confuſion. For thou
doeſt euen now noriſhe within thee, thoſe that
ſhal conſume thee.<note place="margin">Eſai. vij.</note> The Lord hath whiſled for
them out of a farre countrye, and they are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye
come, euen thoſe that ſhall ruynate thine
honour, adnichelat thyne auncient worthines,
and bring thy prayſeworthy fame to ignominy
and ſhame. Oh Sinne, how odible art thou in
the ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt higheſt, that bringeſt ſuch
confuſion vpon them that hath ſo frendly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſed
thee. O Ingland, thou receyuedſt an yl
geſt to herborowe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou waſte contented
that ſynne ſhould lodge with thee: whoſe loue
and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip is the wrath and enmite of God:
whoſe payment and recompence is, captiuitie,
deſtruction and deſolation: for now thy pryde
ſhalbe rewarded with pouertie,<note place="margin">Eſay. iij.</note> thyne abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce
with ſcarcitie, thy gredye purchaſinge
with diſpoſſeſſing.<note place="margin">Eſay. v.</note> Thy ſumptuouſe buylding
with raſing downe, and thyne ambytion with
deſolation: yea the gorgiouſnes of thine appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell
<pb facs="tcp:4739:4"/>
ſhalbe tourned into ragges and ſackcloth:
thyne abundant delicate fare, into famyne and
honger,<note place="margin">Eſay. iij.</note> and the cheriſhed beautye of thy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes
and dayntie Miſtreſſes into wythered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
and ſunne burninge. Theyr fayre layde out
yelowe lockes into baldneſſe, for the tyme ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth
that of force they muſte forgo theyr
trinkettes of pryde, the which at the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
of Gods word they would not abandon,
as are theyr abyllements of gold, tawdrye la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
bongraces, fardingals, tablettes, ringes,
with theyr garded and brodered raymente of
ſundrye faſhions, counterfeyting all nations:
and becauſe theyr huſbandes haue vaynly ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ported
them in the ſame. Theyr bloud ſhalbe
ſhed in the ſtretes, ſayth the Lord. Eſaye. iij.
This ſhalbe the reward of Sinne thy geſt (O
Ingland) beſydes the greuous Idolatry wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in
thou now lyueſt, to the vtter woundinge of
thy conſcientie, agaynſt thy knowledge by y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſye:
the onely meane to accellerat &amp; bring
ſpedye damnation vpon thy head.<note place="margin">Exod. 32. iij. Re. 13.</note> For this
Sinne of ydolatry is ſo odious in Gods ſight
that at no tyme (as teſtifieth the ſcriptures)<note place="margin">Num. 25</note>
hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord lefte the ſame vnpuniſhed: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
be thou moſt certaynly aſſured of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
wrath and indignation, that after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
committing of ſo manye ſinnes, in ſtede of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce
doeſt ende in Idolatrye: yea, it is a
playne argument that thou art forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god,
and geuen ouer into reprobation,<note place="margin">Ier. xliiij</note> for this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſinne (as witneſſeth the Prophetes) that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly<note place="margin">Ezec. vi.</note>
goeth before captiuitie, ſlaughter, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:4"/>
famyne, deſolation and vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
Oh conſyder,<note place="margin">Luke. xv.</note> I pray thee (O Ingland)
how farre thou art alreadye ſtrayed from the
ſhepefold of Chriſt, by one lytle ſtorme of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion.
Oh how cleane art thou blowen awaye
from the port of health, by one bluſtring blaſt
of a buſie Biſhop. Oh how is the ſhippe of thy
comon wealth now toſſed through the vnſkyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes
of one that ruleth the helme. O how are
thy faythfull Chriſtians induced to playe the
diſſemblinge ypocrites, in communicatinge at
vnlawfull ſeruices and blaſphemous ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
by the inſtigation of a fewe vnlearned
Papiſtes.<note place="margin">ij. Tim. ij</note> Wher haſt thou learned in the time
of a ſtorme to abandon the helme,<note place="margin">Math. x.</note> in the tyme
of warre to contracte amyte with the enemyes<note place="margin">i. Pet. iij.</note>
of thy Captayne, and in the tyme of tryall, to
cloke and diſſemble thy fayth? This hath not
the worde of God taught thee, although thou
pretende dyuers excuſes for the ſame: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the loue of thy ſelfe, of the worlde, of thy
goodes and ryches, thy landes and poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
thy wyfe and chyldren, thy fylthy pleaſures,
and fleſhly delites, the which al, thou thinking
by thy diſſimulate ypocriſie to ſaue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,
thou ſhalte moſt certaynly loſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,
as witneſſeth the verytie, ſaying: Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
goeth about by any fraudulent meanes to<note place="margin">Math. x.</note>
ſaue his lyfe,<note place="margin">Mar. viij</note> he ſhall moſt certaynly loſe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame:
yea,<note place="margin">Luke. ix</note> euen this tranſitory lyfe, beſyde the
perpetual damnation of ſoule and body in the
lyfe to come. For the Lord wyl reteyn no ſuch
ſouldiers in his Campe, as ſhall beare a flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:4739:5"/>
face towardes his enemies, and aſſociate
them ſelues with his aduerſaries, he wyl haue
no ſuch ſeruing men in his Court,<note place="margin">iij. Re. 18</note> as ſhall halt
on both ſydes,<note place="margin">Apoc. iij.</note> beyng neyther whote nor cold,
ſekinge to pleaſe two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary mayſters,<note place="margin">Math. vi</note> God,
and Mammon: yea, he accoumpteth all thoſe
pretenſed frendes, for vtter enemyes, that wyl
vyſite the table of deuylles,<note place="margin">i. Corin. x ij. Cor. vi</note> and his alſo: that
ſeke to couple Chriſt with Beliall, lighte with
darkenes, righteouſnes with vnrighteouſnes,
the beleuer with an infydell, and the Temple
of god with Images. In al theſe thinges thou
art coulpable O Inglande, through thy diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate
ypocriſie, in declining from the trueth:
notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thine earneſt promyſe, vowe,
and conſente, to continue a faythfull Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
a trew ſeruaunt, and an vnfayned frend:
for who is he in thee, at this preſent (a few on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
excepted) that ether for feare of men, or loue
of the worlde doeth not abandon the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
impriſoned and exyled congregation of
God, his faythful ſeruauntes, and ioyne him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe
with the company of Idolaters and maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers
hys enemyes? who is he that is not
now contented to abandon the table of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord
the holy communion and Sacrament of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
body and bloud, and to vnyte himſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
that ſacrifycing bloudye aultar of the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
bredde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, the romiſhe Idol? who
is he that doeth not now with all diligence (in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtede
of the lyuely water of Gods holy worde
truely preached) repayre vnto the fylthy pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels
of mennes ſuperſtitious doctrines, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:4739:5"/>
to ſatiſfye theyr thyrſte? yea, who is he
now in thee, that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding before tyme
he condempned with knowledge of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
all maner of Images and Idols, that doth not
now dayly repayre vnto the Temples of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,
in whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany and that before theyr
Idolles, they praye, they knele, they are bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,
they lifte vp theyr handes, they recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
holy water, and holy bread, with dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
exteriour ieſtures of the bodye: And yet
(that worſt is) thei affirme they do not offend
in as muche (as they ſaye) they do it not with
the conſente of theyr harte, but onely with the
outward ieſture of the body, and therefore no
ſinne, in as much as the Lord onely requyreth
the harte,<note place="margin">Roma. x.</note> the whiche they geue vnto hym: as
though there myghte be made a ſeperation of
the ſoule and the body, in dedicatinge the one
vnto the ſeruice of God, and the other to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie:
as though the Lord had not created the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note place="margin">Gene. ij.</note>
both, in vnyting and knytting them together,
making but one man, reſeruing them bothe to
immortalitie:<note place="margin">Deu. 6. 11</note> as though the Lorde God dyd
not earneſtly requyre in his lawe of euery one<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note>
of vs,<note place="margin">Mark. 12</note> our whole ſoule, harte, mynde, ſtrength,
power and outward man:<note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> and yet they contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
to this knowledge, do make a ſeparation,
whereas the Lord hath made ſo perfyte a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction.
But I feare me this theyr ſeparation
tendeth to none other ende, but to deuyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
wholy from God both in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
for he wyl not haue the one without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
neyther is he pleaſed with halfe of hys
<pb facs="tcp:4739:6"/>
creatures. Wherefore yf he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deteſteth whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
fleeth the ſtewes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers:
yf he that hateth ſwering, auoydeth
the felowſhip of blaſphemers: and yf he that
loueth quietneſſe refrayneth the companye of
ruffians &amp; quarellers. How much more ough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt
thou (O dearly beloued) yf thou dydeſt in
dede hate Idolatrye, as thou pretendeſte in
word, to auoyde and flee the companye of all
Idolatres in the committing of theyr Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye:
how much more I ſaye oughteſt thou to
auoyde theyr brothell houſes &amp; ſtewes, theyr
ſinke and puddel of fylthy Idolatrye, &amp; that
not onely with the hart &amp; minde, but alſo with
the body and outward ieſture. For the Lorde
doeth not onely requyre (as wytneſſeth ſaynte
Paul)<note place="margin">Roma. x.</note> the confydence and belefe of the harte
vnto iuſtifycation, but alſo the outwarde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
of the mouth and exteriour conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vnto ſaluation.<note place="margin">Num. xi.</note> Let not the greaſy fleſhpottes
of Egipte, I meane the pleaſures of this lyfe,
ſo muche ſincke into thy mynde, as for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyinge
thereof, thou be contented to abandon
the church of God in the deſert,<note place="margin">ij. Petr. ij</note> and retourne
to thy fylthye puddel agayne. Set rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
thyne eyes the examples of the holye Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes,
Prophetes, Apoſtles, and all other
godly men from the beginning, who all as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſytie
requyred haue abandoned wyllingly
theyr pleaſures,<note place="margin">Ebre. xi.</note> forſaken theyr commodites,
relinquiſhed theyr natyue countrye, haſarded
theyr lyues, ſhedde theyr bloud, and paciently
indured the moſte greuous tormentes of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes
<pb facs="tcp:4739:6"/>
for the teſtimony of the truth, rather
then they would ether in body or in mynd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
with the vngodlye in any vntrueth.
Why rather doeſt thou not practyſe in this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
ſtorme of temptacion, the worthy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
of Daniel, Tobias, Eliezar, Sidrach, Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſech,
and Abednego, with dyuers others,<note place="margin">Dani. vi.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned
in the holy ſcriptures:<note place="margin">Tobie. i. ij. mac. vi</note> who all woulde
geue no place, (as touchinge theyr religion in
the trew worſhipping of God) vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of wicked Princes.<note place="margin">Dani. iij.</note> Then the
examples of Nicodemus,<note place="margin">Ioh. iij.</note> Ioſeph of Arama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,
and Naaman the Syrian,<note place="margin">Ioh. xix.</note> which ſeme to
you to couler your ypocriſy withall.<note place="margin">4. Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But they
beyng rightfully wayed and truely vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded,
meaſured with the lyne of God his holy
word, ſhal lyttle defend your wicked atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes,
but rather dyrectly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute the ſame. The which
thing to accompliſhe, becauſe I of my ſelfe am
vtterly inſufficient and vnable, and for the ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
loue that I beare vnto my natiue country,
whoſe ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſu, I continually
wyſhe for as myne owne. I haue taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me
to reduce into our natyue tounge (according to
my promyſe in my former tranſlated Boke) a
worthye worke that latelye happened into my
handes, no les neceſſarye then profytable and
no les profytable then Godly for this preſent
tyme. The which doeth moſt dyrectly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincyble
aunſwere to all maner of obiections
and wronge alleged examples that may be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duced
for any diſſimularion in religion. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled
iu. iiij. Dialoges, by the faythful ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4739:7"/>
of Ieſus Chriſt, and excellent learned deuine,
Wolfangus Muſculus, for the comfort, edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
and inſtruction of his contryemen the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Germaynes, then oppreſſed by the tyrannye
of Antechriſt in his fylthy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. And nowe
I dedicate the ſame vnto the (O Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) with
theſame mynde for thy ſinguler premonition &amp;
conſolation in theſe thy dayes of aduerſytie &amp;
myſerye, oppreſſed with the lyfe (or rather
greater) Antechriſtian crueltye and tyrannye.
In this Boke are .iiij. Collocutors or ſpeakers
aptly ſet forth of the Author. The fyrſte is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
Euſebius, who according to the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
of hys name occupieth the place of a
faythful Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alwayes perſeuering in the
feare of God, voyde of all diſſimulation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
alwayes a trew and lyuelye fayth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
declining at any tyme fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame, for any
thing that the deuyl, the world, or the fleſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
do, or ymagine. The .ij. is called, Irenius, who
as his name importeth, is all together peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
and a louer of vnyte and concorde, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he perſeuereth in his accuſtomed maner
of lyuing, without caring for any trouble that
ryſeth through any alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he differeth from the other two, in as much
as he doeth not condemne all religion, as doth
the Mondayne, nether yet is he ſo variable as
is the Temporiſour, but for all that he ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
from the rules of a trew Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that
the peace and tranquilitie of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men welth
is more deare vnto him, then is the glorye of
God, the floriſhing of his word, and his own
<pb facs="tcp:4739:7"/>
ſaluacion. The .iij. is named the Temporiſour,
becauſe of his diſſimulation, who obſerueth
more the tyme, then the rules of a Chriſtian,
tendering his owne ſaluation. The laſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Mondayn, that is to ſaye: a worldly man,
or an infydell, who hath neyther God, nor any
religion, in any reputacion. Theſe .iiij. perſons
thou ſhalt heare ſpeake in theſe Dialoges, and
that ſo aptlye and decentlye, that (yf they had
the lyke grace in the Ingliſhe, as they haue in
the Frenche) thou wouldeſt rather iudge them
the lyuely voyces of men then otherwyſe. As
it is, take it in good worth, as a teſtimonye of
my good wyll and earneſt zeale vnto my nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
countrye. Truſting gentle Reader, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
thou haſt diligently peruſed theſame, and
examined it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the touchſtone of Gods word,
and thyne owne conſcience, thou wilt ſearche
no more excuſes to couer thy diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and
impiete withall. For truely ſuche inuented ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes
are manifeſt argumentes of the vtter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
of the ſonne of God and his Kingdom,
as the Parable of thoſe that were inuitated to
the mariage doeth notably teſtifye:<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> wherfore
flee all excuſes,<note place="margin">Luk. xiiij</note> and come vnto the banket now
whyle thou art called, leaſte thou with thyne
excuſes be for euer excluded, and peraduentur
neuer after called agayn.<note place="margin">Mat. xix.</note> Wo worth thoſe oxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
that farme,<note place="margin">Luk. xiiij</note> that wyfe, or anye other earthlye
pleaſure, that ſhall ſtaye vs from comming to
that celeſtiall ſupper, whereas thou ſhalte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
the ſonne of god frendly imbraſing thee,
ſayinge: Come thou bleſſed of my father, and
<pb facs="tcp:4739:8"/>
poſſeſſe the lyfe euerlaſting, mate merye, and
reioyce, the Lord grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you to be found in the
noumbre of thoſe his geſtes in that daye,<note place="margin">Mat. xxij xxv.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
on the wedding garment, &amp; not amongſt
the foliſhe ſlepinge vyrgins, who, hauinge no
reſpect vnto the comming of the brydegrome,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note>
were ſhut out from the mariage,<note place="margin">Mar. xiij</note> whoſe trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant
coming I aſſure you is not farre of,<note place="margin">Luk. xix. xxi.</note> for
the ſignes goyng before theſame, haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
appeared.<note place="margin">ij. Teſſ. ij</note> The ſonne of perdition is reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
Iniquitie hath alreadye the vpperhande,<note place="margin">i. Tim. 4.</note>
The loue of many is abated. What a noumbre
is there that depart from the fayth, in geuing
hede vnto ſpyrytes of errour, and deuyliſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
of them that ſpeake lyes through ypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryſye.
Howe are men nowe become louers of
them ſelues?<note place="margin">ij. Tim. iij</note> Couetous, boaſters, proude, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
ſpeakers, diſobedient, vnthankful, vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
vnkynde, trucebreakers, falſe accuſers, tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours,
highmynded, deſpyſers of them which
are good, gready vpon voluptuouſneſſe more
then the louers of God, hauing a ſimilitude of
godlines, but haue denyed the power thereof:
whoſe madnes is now made apparant vnto al
menne. Theſe are the tokens as wytneſſeth the
ſcriptures, that ſhall immediatly go before his
coming, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloſſome &amp; leaues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fygtree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer. The which toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s yf they haue
lately appeared, or no: I appeale to all mens
conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Wherfore ye holy ones of the lord
reioyce, for the day of your redemption draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
nyghe. And in the meane tyme the Lorde
Ieſus, the onely Sauiour of our ſoules grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4739:8"/>
vnto euery one of vs his holy ſpyrite, to thend
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat we vnderſtandinge theſe thinges maye
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yefullye beare in oure bodyes the mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
of the LORDE Ieſus, to
thend that the lyfe of Ieſus Chriſt
maye appeare in vs, his
grace and peace be
with you all.
AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ R. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogues">
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:9"/>
            <head>¶The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour
(that is to ſaye: the obſeruer of tyme,
or he that chaungeth with the tyme.) Compy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in Latyn by the excellent Clarke Wolfan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus
Muſculus, and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into Frenche by
M. Vallerain Pullain. And out of Frenche in
to Ingliſhe by R. P. 1555.</head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>¶The fyrſt Dialoge.</head>
               <p>¶The perſones or Colocutours are, Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,
the Temporiſour, and Mondayne.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I Cannot ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly coniecture what wyl
be the fynall ende of this ſo peruerſe &amp;
corrupted world. Which is ſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,
ſo wicked and troubleſome, that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
man can fynde no place (no not amonge
thoſe that haue, or ſeme to haue the knowledge
of God) to reſt in. Manye yeares hath it bene
argued and debated, how to knowe the veryte
from the errour, the truth from the lye, and the
light from darkenes, aſwell in the doctryne as
in the Ceremonies of longe tyme vſed in the
Chriſtian church. And this contencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not
bene ſinal, but hath coſt much chriſtian bloud.
The which thing finally could none otherwiſe
be reſolued and brought to paſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
cleauing vnto the holy Scriptures, in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
therin the veryte, taught vnto the world
by Chriſte and his Apoſtles, and that beynge
<pb facs="tcp:4739:10"/>
ones found out, not only reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to imbrace
the ſame, but alſo to forſake all erronious and
ſuperſticious doctrynes, were they neuer ſo
olde, and ſo often confirmed by the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall
authoritie of the Church. The which thing
to bring to paſſe, dyuers excellent perſonages
haue not onely imployed theyr pryuate ſtudye
and labour, but alſo publikely without al feare
haue auaunced theſame, by the ayde and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
of the ordinary Maieſtrates. So that
in dyuers places all Papiſticall doctryne and
ſuperſticious ſeruices were vtterly aboliſhed,
withal theyr falſe conſtitucions, which rather
ſemed an apyſhe maſkinge, then a holy eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall
miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The land of Almayn was
alſo repleniſhed with plentye of good Bokes,
compyled by ſundrye excellente Clarkes, both
learnedly and godly. Yea the noumbre of By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
of the olde and newe Teſtamentes were
infynite: which not onely the learned but alſo
the vulgare people dyd diligently reade. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
where and in euery Temple was contynual
preachinges and ſermons agreing in one vnite
of doctryne. There was no place in the lande
but ye ſhould haue heard ſonge the pſalmes of
Dauid: yea, the wyſdome of God dyd crye in
the ſtretes. And to conclude it ſeemed that in
theſe laſt dayes, the trew religion and the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie
of the auncient Church (ſo longe tyme
defaced) was perfectly reſtabliſhed and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
agayne. But nowe for one lytle myſte and
ſtorme of temptacion, which is ſodenlye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
after ſo longe a caulme and fayre wether,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:10"/>
dyuers are become ſo afrayde that they are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
declyned and fallen backe to thoſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticions
before expelled. And of which noum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre
ſome are ſo reuoulted, that not onely they
do willinglye abandon the verite manifeſtlye
knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo perſiſt in tearing and renting
theſame with theyr abhominable blaſphemes,
to thende it mighte not appeare that they are
turned from God, but from errour and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye,
in making theyr reuoultinge to ſeme no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoulting,
but rather a repentaunce and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliation.
The other ſorte although they vſe no
ſuch blaſphemes agaynſt the truth, but as thei
haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, do kepe it ſecretely hyd in theyr
hartes: yet neuertheleſſe they do not refrayne
to aſſiſte and to preſent at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execrable maſſe
and ſuperſticious ydolatryes, nomore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
fyrſt. And do not onely diſſemble that which
is in theyr hartes, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſte is agaynſt
theyr owne knowledge and conſcience, they do
outwardlye make a ſhowe of that thinge, that
they do not inwardli aproue, but deteſt &amp; hate.
And yet neuertheleſſe in doyng hereof they do
curiouſlye ſearche the meanes to heale the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
gnawing of theyr wounded conſcience.
They wryte to dyuers learned men, to knowe
the certayntie, whether it be lawfull for a man
that hath knowledge, to communicate and be
preſent at the ſuperſticious Ceremonies, or ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
Papiſticall blaſphemes of the vngodlye,
or no? They make ſemblant to enquire of thoſe
thinges as though they dyd not know, what a
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fearing God ought to do, or leaue vndone.
<pb facs="tcp:4739:11"/>
But moſt of theſe do it not becauſe thei would
learne, but rather to thende they mighte fynde
ſome ſtaye and comfort in the abuſing of their
conſciences. But what man is that, that is ſo
ignoraunt of God, and of all religion, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
vnderſtandeth not, that this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no
thing apperteyneth vnto thoſe that truly feare
God? neuertheleſſe I wyl more dyligently fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
henceforth aduyſe my ſelfe, how I maye dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctely
aunſwere thoſe that ſhal interrogate and
queſtion with me hereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot tell what deuyliſhe rage hath of
late occupyed the myndes of a ſort of fooles.
They do complayne of theſe folyes that hath
brought all the worlde in trouble, in the which
alſo there is ſo lytle certytude, that for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace
of theſe .xxx. yeares they haue contended toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
without any agrement, or certaynte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.
And this euyll is not newe. For what tyme
hath there bene, that this ſuperſticious conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion
hath not vexed and troubled the world?
Through a heape of fooliſh queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of God,
of the trew ſeruyce of God, of the truth, of the
religion, and I cannot tell what other fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.
At whom I laughe at pleaſure, withoute
bynding my ſelfe to any maner of religion, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
it be to my commoditie and profyte: and ſo
I fynd my ſelfe moſt at reſt and eaſe, vſing all
thinges at my pleaſure, in caſting a ſyde al ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude
and care, that occurreth and hapneth
by the occaſion of religion. But me thinkes I
ſee yonder my Coſyn Temporiſour, who is in
myne opinion wyſer, then a great manye of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:11"/>
in that he hath without any greate diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
abandoned this new found religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
introduced. For as I remembre it is not paſt
xx. yeares agone, that this fantaſtical newe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
began to budde forth and reuyue. And
then this felow was one of the fyrſt that chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged
his opinion, accordinge as the tyme then
requyred. And hetherto ther hath no euil hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
vnto him therefore, as it hath done vnto
dyuers others. For he hath in euery condicion
ſought to lyue at his eaſe in pleaſure, and hath
wittely wounde him ſelfe oute of many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
wherwith amongſt the reſt he was affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
and that not onely in his outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion,
but alſo inwardly in his conſcience. He
hath nowe perſiſted and continued in this ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie
that they terme (Chriſtian) as long as it
ſerued to his purpoſe and quietnes. But nowe
in as much as he cannot perſeuer therein (the
tyme ſo altering) without ymmynent daunger
both of body and goodes: he loueth rather to
folowe the thing that ſerueth to his commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
then as abedlem to put him ſelfe in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger
for ſo vncerteyne a hope. And therfore now he
beginneth to ſtrike his ſayle, and frameth him
ſelfe vnto the preſent tyme. But herein, he &amp;
I do differ. For I do not care of any maner of
religion, nor any opinions of theſame, nor do
not paſſe a ſtrawe to ſemble or diſſemble in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
maner of thinge that is. But he contrarye
wyſe (although vpon euerye mocion he doeth
chaunge his opinion, accommodating himſelf
vnto the tyme) cannot refrayne his harte from
<pb facs="tcp:4739:12"/>
this conceyued rage, but continually (as a ſort
of other fooles do) tormenteth and vexeth him
ſelfe therwith. And in this he is more vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
and vnquiet, then I am: in that he cannot
all together vnborden him ſelfe of theſe fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
opinions, as I do. And yet neuertheles
he is more wiſe and prudent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other ſort,
the which (I cannot tell for what ſuperſticion
ſake) do ſubmit and geue ouer them ſelues to
a thouſand maner of myſeries &amp; afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
a difficile and perilous lyfe aſwel for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſelues, as theyr frendes: and fynally do fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
dyuers extreame daungers. But now I wyl
call hym. Whence comeſt thou Temporiſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I come from the College, and from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yce
of the blowers and organ players.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mondayne.</speaker>
                  <p>What haſt thou done there, ſeyng that thou
art not accuſtomed to haunt that place?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf I had the lybertie, that I had in tyme
paſt, I would not nowe haunt thoſe ſeruices,
that my conſcience ſo muche abhorreth: but I
am now conſtrayned to do otherwyſe, then I
haue bene accuſtomed, yf I wyl auoyde to fal
into extreame daungers. And thus hath tyme
altered my doynges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayne.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſt wyſelye in myne opinion: for
what haue we to do with thoſe ſtrifes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
that are ryſen vp in our dayes, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt
the wyſe vayne and ydle perſons? Lette vs
obeye thoſe that rule, and haue the auctorite to
<pb facs="tcp:4739:12"/>
ordre theſe thinges, and can do vnto vs good
or euyl, wel or wo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſo I do, and ſo lyue in quietneſſe as
concerning the world. But for all that, my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
is wonderfully troubled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayne.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore I pray thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſteſt thou that? Doeſt not thou knowe
that thoſe ſinne greuouſly that do any thinge
agaynſt theyr conſcience?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayne.</speaker>
                  <p>That is nothing els but a dreame of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theo
logians, which I haue oftentymes hearde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
but I praye thee, conſider dyrectly what
maner of conſcience thou haſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it as be maye, I ſinne as often as I do
any thing agaynſt the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayne.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyl not entre in diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the qualitie of the conſcience: but I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
of thee, yf thou thinke that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
and Maieſtrates that conſtrayne thee to
go to the ſeruyces of the Papiſtes, are not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
thereunto by theyr conſciences: to wytte,
to reſtabliſhe by theyr power and auctorytie,
the olde accuſtomed Religion, that hath bene
aboliſhed theſe certayne yeares?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll not denye, but that it maye be, that
ſome of them do it, theyr conſciences mouinge
them thereunto: but it cannot be alſo denyed,
that dyuers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſo lyue, that it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
to iudge whether they haue any conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
or feare of God, or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:13"/>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou mayſt not for all that doubt, but that
they are conſtituted in auctoritie, and haue
power ouer theyr ſubiectes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I do acknowledge and allowe theyr power
and auctoritie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>What maner of conſcience then haſt thou,
that refuſeſt to obeye the hygher powers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not al together refuſe that, but rather
thinke that they ought to be obeyed onelye in
worldly matters, and ſecular cauſes, and not
in religion. I thinke certainly they haue aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
in temporall regimentes, but not in mens
conſciences, which are ſubiect vnto one onely
God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou abuſeſt thy ſelf, wherfore laye a ſyde
this thy fooliſhe and ſcrupelous conſcience, &amp;
deſiſte from all care and penſyfnes of mynde,
which conſumeth thy body without any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
or purpoſe. And know this, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrates
haue receyued auctorytie ouer all
thinges: they haue in this worlde all maner of
power and preeminence. Art thou ignoraunte
of this ſaying: (<hi>Dimidium imperij cum</hi> Ioue Ceſar
habet.) Iupiter and Ceſar haue the Empire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded
betwene them. And becauſe thou ſhalte
not reiecte this, as the ſaying of a Panym: ſee
how the ſcripture confyrmeth it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> The heauen
is the Lordes, but as for the earth he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
it vnto the chyldren of men. God hath no
maner of care of theſe thinges that he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:4739:13"/>
vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of thoſe that he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
yned Monarches and Gouernours of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orld: to thend they may at theyr pleaſure or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eyne
the ſtate of religion, as it ſhal ſeme vnto
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem expedient for the better ordre and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ent
of theyr ſubiectes, and to them we muſte
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>beye in all thinges. Furthermore thou haſt a
wyfe and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ouer whom by the appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
of God thou haſte eſpeciall charge: by
what conſcience then I praye thee (ſeyng thou
doeſt ſo often alledge thy conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) canſt thou
abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and forſake them, in withdrawing thy
helpe from them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue nede of thee?
Furthermore thou haſt thy neyghbours, with
whom thou art bound to lyue in peace &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilite,
as yf thou wart but one bodi with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
With what conſcience canſt thou then refuſe
theyr honeſt requeſt to remayn and dwel with
them, and do as they do? See howe thou arte
circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented and incloſed on euery ſyde. Aboue
thee is the auctorite of the Maieſtrate, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
thou knoweſt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeſt we ought to obey.
Equal by thy ſyde is thy wyfe, who is ſtrayt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
commended vnto thee of God. Vnderneth
thee are thy chyldren and familie, who all as
right requyreth, cal vpon thee for thy help. Yf
thou then do abandon and withdraw thy hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
hand from them, haſt thou not falſifyed
thy fayth, as often tymes thy preachers haue
taught thee? Neare vnto thee are thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
to whom thou oughteſt to be fyrinelye
vnited, as one membre with another. I omitte
here what thou oweſt of duetye vnto thy ſelf:
<pb facs="tcp:4739:14"/>
wherfore then without any occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeſt thou
ſo much afflicte and diſquyet thy ſelf in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
ſo apparant, for a lytle folyſhe and ſcrupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
conſcience ſake? Folowe rather my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayl:
frame thy ſelfe vnto the wyl and pleaſure
of the Maieſtrates, not onely by an outwarde
ſimulation, as I ſee thou doeſt, but alſo with
the inward mocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of thy harte, and leaue thoſe
diſputacions vnto the learned deuynes &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
Maieſtrates: yf thei thinke mete to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
olde thinges, wel, obey thou, let it ſuffyſe thee
that thou haſte bene of that ſecte and opinion
theſe .xx. yeares. Yf they thinke it expedient to
reſtabliſhe auncient cuſtomes, and to redyfye
agayne that whiche of late hath bene ruyned,
content thy ſelfe lykewyſe: yf they make anye
inhibicions, beware thou do not tranſgreſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt
them: yf they commaunde any thinge,
obeye the ſame: and by this meanes thou ſhalt
pleaſe all men, and ſhalt be reputed prudente,
diſcrete and well aduyſed: &amp; ſo thyne affayres
and ſubſtaunce ſhall remayne in peace &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie,
and ſhalt poſſeſſe theſame in quietnes:
for what follye is it to do that thinge by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynte
and compulſion that thou mayeſt do
willingly, and although thou would eſt not do
it, yet ſhalte thou be compelled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely thy counſayl is very pleaſaunt and
agreable vnto the fleſhe, but for all that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt
not as yet healed the wound of my conſcience.
This is a good counſayl to concerue and kepe
my goodes, but my conſcience doeth vtterlye
<pb facs="tcp:4739:14"/>
reponge agaynſt it. For all that thou haſt alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
of the auctorytie of the Maieſtrates and
Princes, and then of my wyfe, chyldren and
neyghbours, is not according to the worde of
God, as I could ſufficiently proue by dyuers
obiections. But I perceyue yonder Euſebius,
who is a man truely fearing God, and louing
pure religion. I wil ſpeake with him, we muſt
make a little haſte, for he goeth apace, he hath
ſome boke in his hand, it may be that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
forthe to walke abroade to recreate hys
mynde in meditating ſome good thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>What occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moueth thee to go vnto him,
he is a ſimple ſuperſticious Idiote? There is
no doubt but the boke that he hath in his hand
is a new Teſtament, that is to ſay: the doctrine
of ſuperſticion where withall the worlde is
troubled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>For all thy ſayinges: I wyll go to hym.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll go alſo, to heare what theſe fooles
ſhal deuyſe together, &amp; learne by what meanes
they do thus torment theyr conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Heareſt thou Euſebe? Stay a lytle, yf thy
buſynes requyre not to much haſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yonder commeth he that I haue dyuers
tymes deſyred to talke withall,<note place="margin">Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to himſelfe.</note> to proue yf I
coulde reduce him into the righte waye: but I
feare me it is but loſt laboure, for he is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte
Temporiſour as well in name as in facte,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:15"/>
ſuche a one as beleueth for a tyme, and when
temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh, wythereth away. And more
ouer me thinke I ſee with him his Coſyn Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayn,
a man allienated and deuyded from all
religion. But for as muche as he calleth me, I
wyll ſtaye, and ſee what he would haue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether goeſt thou, Euſebe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Into the feldes to walke, to recreate my
ſpryte. What wilt thou haue with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Of longe tyme I haue purpoſed to come &amp;
vyſite the at thy houſe, to confarre with the of
this miſerable ruyne of oure religion, whiche
thing troubleth my ſprytes ſo much, that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt
neyther night nor daye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf it pleaſe thee, let vs retourne then to my
houſe together?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I am right well contente. What wilte thou
do Mondayn?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf I wiſt I ſhould not offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you, I would
be gladly with you at your communication?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhalbe contented for my parte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>And I reiecte noman: much leſſe then wyll
I refuſe a neyghbour. And as the trueth is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
vnto light, euen ſo is ſhe not afrayde to
ſhyne and appeare before al maner of perſons.
God wylleth, that we do aſſemble together in
his name, &amp; hath promyſed to be in the middes
<pb facs="tcp:4739:15"/>
of vs, I wyll go in before, folowye both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Peace be vnto this houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>And to all thoſe that entre in. Come let vs
go in yonder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>How manye bokes,<note place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forth Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayn ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth as it were to him ſelf, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do not aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g paſſinge on his ſay inges. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo we maye not caſt pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les before ſwyne. &amp;c</note> and how litle houſhold
ſtuffe? Is there a more foole then this man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Sitte downe at this Table.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>We wyll, ſeyng thou biddeſt vs. Sit thou
downe alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>I hadde leuer ſit at a table furniſhed with
wyne, then with bokes. I ſee nothing here but
papers, I would to God the rattes and myce
had eaten them all: for and theſe bokes were
not, we ſhould lyue in more peace in the world
then we now do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Graunt O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that we may
profite in ſome thing to the glory of thy name.
Now Temporiſour ſaye what thou wilt, and
we wyl heare thee, and communicate together
frely euery one according to his conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet agayne this conſcience, what deuyl in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented
that name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt verye well Euſebius, what
my ſubſtaunce is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it to be very great, the Lord grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4739:16"/>
that thou vſe it wel, and that thou mayeſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe
it, and it not thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt alſo what a noumbre of chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren
I haue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord increaſe them, and kepe them to
his glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>O foole what haſt thou to do with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of God? Thinke of thyne owne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I deſyre eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame withal my hart. Thou
knoweſt furthermore in what reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am
in, with the Burgeſes and Maieſtrates.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſt wel to thinke of theſe thinges,
beware that thou doeſte not haſarde them to
much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I knowe all thoſe thinges, my frend Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Now am I come to this yſſewe, eyther to
haſard and forſake all together, or els to ioyne
my ſelf with other men, in being preſent at the
papiſticall ſeruices and ſuperſticions by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation.
Wherefore I beſeche thee in the
name of God, that thou wilt tell me thyne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe,
yf it be lawefull without offence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
to him that knoweth the veritie of the
holy ſcriptures, to be preſent at the papiſticall
ſuperſticious ſeruices through the compulſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of his ſuperiours?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>What a fooliſhe queſtion is this to enquire
(yf it be lawfull) when that neceſſite and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynt
teacheth him, what he ought to do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:16"/>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou mayeſt eaſelye gather myne aduyſe
herein, by that which thou ſeeſt me do, for I do
that, that I thinke to be the beſt, yf I had here
in a better iudgement, truely I woulde put it
in practyſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf thou wart in his place thou wouldeſt do
otherwyſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee wel what thou doeſt. Thou doeſt kepe
thy ſelfe from coming to any of the papiſticall
ſeruyces. But that notwithſtanding I deſyre
to know yf I may not be there without finne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf thou mighteſt ſo be there, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo would
I, and alſo all other that nowe abſtayne them
ſelues thence: for I thinke it nomore lawefull
for thee to be there, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for me. But fyrſt let me
vnderſtand how thou doeſt behaue thy ſelf in
this poynt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>How that I do behaue my ſelf? I do obeye
the ordinaunces of the Maieſtrates, &amp; I come
to theyr ſeruices according as they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Therein thou doeſt not fooliſhly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it trew? Doeſt thou fyrſt of al the thing
that they commaunde thee: and then aſke yf it
be well done? Why dyddeſt thou not rather
fyrſt aſke, what had bene the duetye of a man
fearing God, and after thou hadſt knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame,
to haue putte it in practyce? Doeſt thou
not remembre this olde ſentence: fyrſte deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne,
and then put in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? But thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:4739:17"/>
done cleane contrarye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>He hath done both wyſely and aduyſedly,
according to the preſente neceſſitie: but in the
other thinge he hath done fooliſhly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſayd wel, but I was forced to do
as I dyd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherto then ſerueth it to aſke counſayl, yf
it be lawefull, or no, ſeyng thou art reſolued to
do the thing that they compell thee? Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
belongeth vnto thoſe that are about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne
a thing, the thing beyng as yet nether
done, nor begon: beyng in theyr facultie either
to do, or vndo: thoſe (I ſaye) may receyue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte
by conſulting and inquiring thereof. But
ſeyng that thou haſt loſt this libertie, by thine
owne folye, I cannot perceyue to what ende &amp;
purpoſe thou moueſt this queſtion, after it is
done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>It is without all ordre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not putte from this lybertie, but as I
ſayd before, I am forced to do that the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
commaundeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf thou be a chriſtian man, thou canſt not
be compelled to do an vnlawfull thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>This felow is out of his wyt: yf he cannot
be compelled, no man would compell him: but
they do conſtrayne him, ergo he maye be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:17"/>
                  <p>What can I not be compelled?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>All theyr commaundementes haue a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
annexed thereunto, to wytte, yf anye man
wyll not obeye, that he be puniſhed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mayſt thou chuſe, ether to do that they
commaunde, or els to endure and ſuffre that
which the condicion annexed thereunto doeth
threaten. Thou mayſt chuſe then, one or other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I knowe all this to be trew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Seyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thou mayſt chuſe according
to thy pleaſure, how canſt thou ſaye then, that
thou art conſtrained: There can be no compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
whereas there is election.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot denye it: but it is daungerous to
fall into the handes of thoſe that may oppreſſe
and ſubdue me. For feare whereof, I do that
they commaunde me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Wyſely done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>But it is a greater matter to fal into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
of the lyuing god, that is of power not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to kyll the body, but alſo to caſt the ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
hell fyre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe felowes are afrayde of ſhadowes.
They prate of a fyre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet euer ſawe,
and in the meane tyme they fall into burninge
flammes that apparantly conſumeth them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:18"/>
                  <p>Thou ſayeſt well. But I am ſo feble that I
am not able to endure the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they
threaten me withall, yf I do not obeye them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I knowe that the ſpyryte is readye, but the
fleſhe is weake. But for all that we are not to
be excuſed, yf through infyrmitie we do anye
thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greatly offendeth the Maieſtie of god:
we ought rather to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine of this infirmitie,
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeeke meanes to excuſe &amp; couer the ſame.
Let vs purely confeſſe our ſynne, and not ſeke
to hyde it, praying the Lord continually to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
and confyrme our fayth. But let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceade
further: I demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely my frend
Temporiſour, what thou thinkeſt in thy harte
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art preſent with the papiſtes at their
ſeruices? Thou dydſt aſke of me eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now, yf it
be lawfull for thee to be there. But what aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth
thy conſcience to my queſtion? Thou
canneſt not be ignoraunt therof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Seynge thou aſkeſte me of my conſcience
Euſebie, I cannot denye but fyrſt of al before
I wente vnto the papiſticall ſeruices my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
dyd inceſſantlye admoniſhe me that I
ſhould not go thyther. She ſayde that this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
and coniunction with the vngodlye, was
nothinge els but a manifeſt renouncinge of the
veritie knowen, and a confyrmation of all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion.
She threatened me alſo with the
greate indignation and wrathe of almightye
GOD, yf I dyd ſo. And that I ſhoulde fall
thereby into execrable blyndneſſe, and other
<pb facs="tcp:4739:18"/>
horryble euylles. And after I had bene there,
ſhe accuſed me of my facte, and that at the firſt
tyme verye ſharpely: but after that euery tyme
that I went, leſſe then other: ſo that nowe in a
maner I fele in my conſcience no repugnaunce
of my goyng thether.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>O Temporiſour, yf thou ſayeſt truely, then
arte thou in the waye of reprobation, oute of
the which thou ſhalte not be able to eſcape, yf
thou doeſt not forthwith withdraw thy ſelfe:
for it is a heauy burthen, the condemnation of
oure owne conſcience: and it is verye daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
to expreſſe and expell the fyrſte mocions
and pryckinges thereof, euen the nexte waye
to make the harte all together incenſyble and
withoute all vnderſtandinge. And what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreſte
thou nowe Temporiſour, but that I
woulde take awaye theſe gnawinges and pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinges
of thy conſcience, by affyrminge that
thou mayeſt ſurelye and lawefullye go vnto
theyr ſuperſtycious ſeruyces, to thende that
thou mayeſt nowe doe the ſame wyth a quyet
conſcience, that before thou dyddeſte wyth a
ſorowefull harte. Yf thou deſyre to knowe
nothinge but thys, thou neadeſte not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre
of me, for thou haſte a teacher in thyne
owne boſome, that is ſufficientlye able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe
thee in that behalfe. For by thine owne
proper iudgemente thou doeſte the thing that
perteyneth not vnto a Chriſtian man to doe:
and yet thou aſkeſte whether thou doeſt well
or euyll.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:19"/>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>In all my lyfe I neuer ſawe more greater
fooles, peſtring and troublinge themſelues ſo
vnadúyſedly about vanitie and follie. Were it
not better all together to withdraw our ſelues
from all opinion of God and of religion, then
to wrap our ſelfes in theſe troubles?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou killeſt me Euſebie, thou doubleſt my
grefe. Before I moſt myſerably tormented my
ſelfe with myne owne iudgement, and now in
ſeking helpe, I fynd preſent death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I am moued to pytye, to behold thy myſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble
ſtate, and not onely thyne, but all other our
poore brethren, that are oppreſſed with ſuche
anguiſhes, by the wickednes of ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or by
theyr ſuperſticions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Youre myſerye proceadeth not from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion
of other, but of yourſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Leaue, I pray thee theſe thinges, and come
to the yſſewe: what knoweſt thou yf the Lord
wyll extende his mercye hereafter towardes
me: Do not repute me amongeſt the noumbre
of thoſe that haue nomore hope of ſaluation, I
cannot yet diſpayre of the grace of God. But
now (I pray thee) aunſwere directely vnto my
queſtion: and as touching that, that bordeneth
my conſcience, let vs omitte it for a whyle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Hitherto I haue heard the purpoſe of your
<pb facs="tcp:4739:19"/>
communication together: but for aſmuch as I
am come hyther, nether to diſpute, nor to iudge
but onely to heare, I wyll leaue you in youre
diſputacion. Onely there is one thing wherof
I wyll admoniſhe you. Remembre alwayes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
neceſſitie is a heauy burthen. And now I leaue
you, for I haue other more greater affayres.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>My frend, we wyll not kepe thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyne
affayres. But thou Temporiſour, what wylt
thou do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Seyng that this my neyghbour wil depart
I cannot with myne honeſty ſuffre him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
home alone, but wyl go with him, and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terward
wyll returne agayne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll tarye thy comming. But I pray thee
(yf it be poſſible) bring with thee thy frend I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renius,
for he is a gentyll perſon, and is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
alienated from religion: and alſo the
noumbre of three is more perfecte, and more
mete for ſuch a collation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll bringe hym, yf I can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Mondayn.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon me Euſebie in that I do departe,
and breake the purpoſe of youre communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
Yf I can do you any pleaſure towardes the
Maieſtrates of the cytie, lette me knowe it,
and ye ſhall commaunde me, I wyll not fayle.
I am yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:20"/>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I moſt hartely thanke you. Thou Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſour,
come agayne quickely: leaſt ſupper tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
approching we be conſtrayned to leaue our
diſputacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll come agayne ſtrayghtway.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>☞The ende of the Dialoge.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:20"/>
               <head>❀The ſecond
Dialoge.</head>
               <p>☞The Collocutors. The Temporiſour.
Ireneus, and Euſebius.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I Was verye yll aduyſed, when I procured
Mondayn to heare oure diſputacion. In
mine opinion he is a very wicked man: it is
to be feared that he wyll vtter all oure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
vnto the Maieſtrates. Wel, an
other tyme I wyll be better aduyſed. I wyll
make ſpede to cal Ireneus: he is accuſtomed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
this tyme of the daye commonlye to be at
home. I wyll ſee yf he be there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Some body knocketh at the gate. Boye, go
open the dore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>What doeſt thou Ireneus?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing, but loke here in an olde boke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>For aſmuch as thou haſt no great buſynes,
would it not pleaſe thee to accompanye me to
the houſe of Euſebius?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Irenius.</speaker>
                  <p>What to do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>To deuyſe and commune together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Paraduenture he is not at leaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, that he is. And in ſo doyng thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:4739:21"/>
do him great pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I wyl go with thee, I wyl not refuſe
the company and communicati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll go in before to leade thee the waye,
for I am better acquaynted with thys houſe
then thou. I am here Euſebie, and here is alſo
Ireneus. Yf there be nothing happened ſince,
let vs purſew our former communication.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>There is ſome thing happened ſince youre
beyng here, but what then? it behoueth vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s
to prefarre thoſe thinges that concerne
our ſaluacion, before all other matters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf there be any ſecrete matter betwixt you,
I wyll withdraw my ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>There is nothinge ſo ſecrete amongeſt vs,
but we can be contented to communicate the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame
vnto thee. We began not long ago to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute:
yf it be lawfull for a man, knowing the
worde of God, to be preſent at the papiſticall
ſeruices. And this queſtion was fyrſte moued
by oure frend here Temporiſour, and for thys
cauſe is he come hyther nowe, to vnderſtande
myne aduyſe herein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye knowe righte well both of you, howe I
haue alwayes behaued my ſelfe in this variete
of religion. Seking nothing ſo much as to liue
in peace and quietneſſe, for the mayntenaunce
whereof I haue contemned neither of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:
but vſed my ſelfe with indifferencye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:4739:21"/>
them both, hauinge alwayes thys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,
that by ſome good meanes theſe quarelles
might be qualified, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencions accorded,
that ſo much do alienate the hartes of the faith
full, and cauſe the wycked an vnbeleuers to
mocke our chriſtianite. And with the like good
wyll I wyll be preſent at this your collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yf
it pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Syt here then. Aſſiſte vs O Chriſt by thy
holy ſpyryte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Now yf it pleaſe thee Euſebie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
the matter, whereof we talked a lyttle
before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyl do it gladly, with this conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
ye both with me, wyl dyligently conſyder this
matter, not as a thinge particularely appertey
ninge vnto one, but as a matter common to all
perſones, to thende that priuate affection and
ſelfe loue, do leade vs to nothinge beſyde the
trueth. And for aſmuch as by this our collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
our purpoſe is not to ſearche out abare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
without effecte, but rather a perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
ſuche as apperteyneth to God and to
his trueth: Tell me therfore (I pray thee) Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poriſour,
before we go any further in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<note place="margin">Nota.</note>
what reuerence thou wilte beare vnto the
trueth, when thou ſhalt be made to knowe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame,
without any contradiction?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherto ſerueth this queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Whereto? I wyl tell thee at ones. To thend
we would not labour in vayne, for the glorye
<pb facs="tcp:4739:22"/>
of God, and thy ſaluation: for wherto ſhall it
ſerue to beate the eyre with our wordes? Yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
be not reſolued in thy conſcience, (after thou
knoweſt the truth) to frame thy lyfe according
vnto the ſame in refuſing al vnlawful thinges?
Whereto ſhall we ſpende ſo manye wordes in
vayne: And not onelye in vayne, but rather to
prouoke the iudgemente of God to fall more
greuouſly vpon thee, and to incenſe his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
agaynſt the. Art thou ignoraunt of this
ſayinge of Chriſt: The ſeruaunt knowing, and
not doyng, ſhalbe greuouſly puniſhed? &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
fyrſt of all determyne with thy ſelfe what
thou wylte do, when thou ſhalte knowe, what
thing is commaunded, and what thinge is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hybited.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Now can I promyſe any thing before hand
what I wyll do, ſeynge it is not in myne owne
power, but cometh of the grace of god: Leaue
that then to the grace of God, and beginne as
I haue deſyred thee, to conſydre and examyne
this matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not demaund (O Temporiſour) what
thing thou wylt do, hauing knowen the truth,
but wherto thou art preſently inclyned? I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
not of the thing to come, but what the
intencion of thyne harte is nowe. It is two
thinges, to ſay what thou purpoſeſt to do, and
to ſay what thou ſhalt do. As touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thinges
to come: It behoueth him that hath a good wil
and is already inclined to godlines, to aſke the
grace of God for the performau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſame.
But where as there is no wyl, nor determined
<pb facs="tcp:4739:22"/>
purpoſe, to do the thinges that are godli: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth
him fyrſte of all to deſyre God to geue
him a wyll to do well, who onelye (as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
the Apoſtle) accompliſheth and worketh
in vs as well the wyl, as the dede. Proteſt and
expreſſe therfore here (O Temporiſour) what
wyl thou haſt preſently, to thend that I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and vnderſtanding the ſame, may wade in
this matter accordingly. I pray thee Ireneus,
is not this my requeſt reaſonable? Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not denye it. For who is ſo much a beaſt
that doeth not well perceyue the great follye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
reſteth in him that is ſycke, who continuallye
calleth for the phiſition, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath him,
wyl not folow his counſayl? Temporiſour.</p>
                  <p>Yet I cannot expreſſe, what I haue purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to do, ſo much am I perplexed in my mind,
which is as yet inclyned hether and thether,
without any reſolued determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
wyll ſettle my mynde to ſome good
ende, after that I am aduertyſed and reſolued
of the truth: &amp; therfore I pray the (O Euſebie)
proceade vnto the matter. Euſebius.</p>
                  <p>The condition of mans mynde is very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
when that onely we knowe not what we
ſhall do hereafter, but that leaſt is, we are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt
of that we wyll preſentlye. But go to
my frende Temporiſour, for aſmuche as thou
art not able to make declaration of thy wyl, at
leaſt wayes declare vnto vs, what it is that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
deſyreſt withall thy hart: thou ſhalt fynde dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
that do complayne that they cannot feale
in themſelues no determyned purpoſe &amp; wyll:
<pb facs="tcp:4739:23"/>
and therfore do vnfaynedly wiſhe and deſyre,
that they maye haue ſuche a purpoſed wyll as
they do not as yet feale in theyr hartes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I do moſt earneſtly deſyre a ſtabliſhed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
and wyll. But to affirme that I haue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame
all ready in my harte, I dare not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf thy deſire be ſuche, that thou mayſt ones
ſettle thy harte and mynde thorowely, in that
thing, wherin it is not as yet ſtabliſhed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hou
haſte no cauſe to diſpayre, but rather to praye
vnto God oure father, to ſtabliſhe in thy harte
this purpoſe to wyll well, and fynally to leade
thee vnto the trew and perfect deſyre and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
of godlynes by wel doyng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyl dyligently fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow thy counſayl: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
I deſyre thee to helpe me with thy prayers.
But I pray thee now beginne to aunſwere my
preſent queſtion. Euſebius.</p>
                  <p>I wyll moſt gladly ſatiſfye thy requeſte in
both.<note place="margin">Thre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> Fyrſt of all it is moſt certayn, that there
are three maner of communications in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
The one is neceſſary and of neceſſitie. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is indifferent and lawefull. The thyrd is
neyther lawefull nor indifferent, but all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
vnlawful and prohibyted. In the firſt are
compryſed al thoſe thinges without the which
no man can be ſaued: and in this part, this que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
hath no place, to wytte, whether the thing
be lawfull, or no? Temporiſour.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe the ſame. But what are thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:4739:23"/>
thinges that are of neceſſitie neceſſary?<note place="margin">Thynges neceſſary</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>The trew and perfect knowledge of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
father, and of his ſonne whom he hath ſente,
Ieſus Chriſt. The trewe lyuely fayth, and the
confeſſion of the ſame, vnfayned repentaunce,
lawfull obedience, feare and reuerence of god,
inuocation &amp; prayer with faith, hope of good
thinges to come, patience in perſecution and
affliction, trewe and perfect loue of God, and
of our neyghbours,<note place="margin">Out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ther is no ſaluation</note> &amp; other lyke thinges, with
out the which we cannot be ſaued. For by the
communicating of theſe thinges, we do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
with all the electe of God, without
whoſe company and felowſhip there is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
to be hoped for. Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>There are very few Euſebie that do enquire
after this maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. Euſebius</p>
                  <p>So much is the world blinded. The ſeconde
maner of communication is, as I ſayd before,
indifferent, tollerable, and lawfull, herein are
compryſed all thoſe thinges, that are free, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
and lawfull. Temporiſour.</p>
                  <p>What are they? Euſebius.</p>
                  <p>All thoſe thinges that are not of them ſelues
agaynſt the worde of grace, which is the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell:
to wyte, meate, drinke, clothing, obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of dayes, and all other obſeruations, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
which the puritie of the chriſtian fayth is not
violated nor defyled. To communicate in theſe
thinges with the faythfull, yf it be free, it is
alſo lawfull: and yf it tende to charitie, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
expedient.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:24"/>
                  <p>What is that, that thou ſayeſt: yf it be free,
it is alſo lawfull? Euſebius.</p>
                  <p>I ſayd it meaning thereby to exclude all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye,
by the which thoſe thinges that of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſelues are free, to do them, or to leaue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
(of the whiche alſo we haue receyued no
commaundement of God) are neuertheleſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded
to be done vnder the payne of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſinne: wherby the conſciences of the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
which ought to be free, are made captyue
and bonde to the commaundementes of men.
For I affyrme that thoſe thinges haue vtterly
loſt theyr freedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that otherwyſe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues
are free, when that eyther through coſtume, or
lawes they are commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be obſerued as
thinges neceſſary (as witneſſeth the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 2</note>)
Let noman (ſayth he) trouble your conſcience,
about meate, or drinke, or a pece of a holy day,
&amp;c. And afterwarde (he ſayth) ye are redemed
with a great pryce, make not your ſelfes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the bond ſeruauntes of men. Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>Some would here reply agaynſt you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat
the wordes of the Apoſtle to the Colloſſians
by you aledged, do nothinge ſerue to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.
In aſmuche as he doeth not there ſpeake
any thing of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the church
but of the commaundementes of the Moyeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
lawe: for aſmuch as in his tyme ſome went
about to make thoſe commaundementes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>It is trewe, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh there
of the obſeruation of the lawe: but I pray thee
conſydre, yf there be anye reaſon, to bynde the
<pb facs="tcp:4739:24"/>
conſciences of men by the commaundementes
of Biſhops: ſeyng that the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
of the lawe do not bynd them, which were not
eſtabliſhed by men, but by God? Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>I maynteyne nothing: but I haue alledged
that nowe, that here tofore I haue heard of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
men, onely adding there vnto this worde.
That thoſe commaundementes that thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
the Biſhoppes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Church.</note> other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
cal them the commaundementes of the church,
and therfore neceſſarye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>That inquyre thou of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>But thou Temporiſour, what is thyne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
herein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>No church of Chriſt hath any auctorite to
commaunde in the houſe of God,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> but onely to
obeye. For ſhe is the wyfe, and not myſtreſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>As a wyfe ſhe is ſubiecte to obeye her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
who is Ieſus Chriſt: and yet for all that
ſhe ceaſeth not to haue auctoritie ouer hyr chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
to commaunde them: ſo ſay our Doctors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it well ynough. But I praye thee,
which be hyr chyldren to whom ſhe may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke, all thoſe that be Chriſtians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Who is then, this commaundinge church,
yf al chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are but the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church?
I ſuppoſed that the church is ſo compyled and
and knyt together of Chriſtians, as the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:4739:25"/>
is, of certayn me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. But theſe people ſpeake
as yf there were ſome one churche by it ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
hath auctoritie to commaunde all chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
as hyr chyldren. Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>They call this church Catholyke and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall.<note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke church.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>In this church is comprehended al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
people. Yf this be the church that they meane,
I would gladly know in what place was there
euer this catholyke and vniuerſall aſſemble of
chriſtians: in the whiche was ordeyned theſe
commaundementes, that they cal the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes
of the church? Ireneus.</p>
                  <p>It is not poſſible that all Chriſtian people
could aſſemble together in one place. But they
ſay: that the Romayne church is abled into the
place therof, ſo that all that euer ſhe ordeyned,
is auctoryſed as yf it were done by the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall
church. Euſebius.</p>
                  <p>They ſaye ſo: but howe do they proue it?
Who hath geuen the Churche of Rome thys
power?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>We go cleane fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our matter: let vs referre
this queſtion of the auctoritie of the churche
vnto another tyme, and returne to oure former
purpoſe, from the which we haue ſtrayed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſayeſt wel. Tel me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Temporiſour,
doeſt thou reken and place the papiſticall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices
amongeſt thoſe thinges that are free, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,
and lawefull, or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>The papiſtes themſelues do not ſaye, that
<pb facs="tcp:4739:25"/>
thei are free and indifferent, but neceſſary: but
as for me, I do not exteme them amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt thoſe
thinges that are lawful and free, but rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt
thoſe that are prohybyted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt geuen a good iudgement. Let vs
now come to the thyrd maner of communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the which we call prohibyted or forbode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here
in are compryſed all thoſe thinges that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the worde of God, as are all falſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyces,
ſuperſticions, mennes decrees without
the auctoritie of the worde, inuocation of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaynctes,
and ſuche other lyke conſtitucions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Amongeſt the which noumbre, I iudge the
papiſtical ſeruyces to haue place, of the which
now we are in queſtion, wherfore tell me yf it
be lawfull by any meanes to participate at the
ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I geue you leaue to iudge in theſe thinges
as it ſhall ſeme vnto you good, although I can
not accorde there vnto with you, yet I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentend
to heare what concluſion you wyl make
of this queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende thy modefiye, Irenie: but come
on Temporiſour, thou aſkeſt yf it be lawful by
any meanes to communicate and be preſent at
vnlawfull ſeruyces. Fyrſte tell me what thou
meaneſt by this, by any meanes? wherfore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
doeſt not thou playnly demaunde, yf it be all
together lawfull to communicate all maner
of wayes at theſe vnlawfull ſeruyces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:26"/>
                  <p>I vnderſtand that there are<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers</note> .ij. maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications:
one is, in opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wyl, affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;
mynd. The other is only outwardly as it were
in a certayne outward behauiour: &amp; foraſmuch
as my communication is, neyther in opinion,
wyll nor mynd, but only in outward ieſture, I
do not aſke therfore, whether euerye maner of
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication be lawful (for I know the fyrſte
to be altogether vnlawfull,) but I requyre to
know yf it be lawfull to communicate by anye
meanes, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding therby the outward ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciete
and communication.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thinkeſt thou that thou doeſt not ſinne at
all, by this outward ſociete and coniunction w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
the vngodly in their ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becauſe thou
doeſt not inwardly conſent thereunto?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe ſo: and therefore I make inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Geue me leaue Temporiſour, to ſaye myne
opinion. Thou ſemeſt vnto me to do in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,
as yf one beyng apprehended amongeſt
theues in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting of theyr robberyes, would
excuſe himſelf before the iudge that he dyd not
ſteale, alledging that he ſtale with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt
hys harte and mynd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſpeakeſt very rudelye: and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe,
thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateſt aſwel as I, at theſe
papiſtical ſeruices, outw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is trew, &amp; inwardly alſo, &amp; doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
my ſelf in ſo doynge, for I exteme that
to be laweful, that ye ſay to be vnlawful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:26"/>
                  <p>Although Ireny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy laſt ſaying be falſe &amp;
vntrew, yet dyddeſt thou before (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
applye not farre amis the compariſon of
the theſe vnto the facte and queſtion of tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſour.
But tell me now Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poriſour, yf in theſe
papiſticall ſeruices, ſhere were committed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulteryes,
thefte, and effuſion of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud,
wouldeſt thou be preſent at them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>No, although I were conſtrayned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I could not be there without ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou canneſt not be without ſinne (as thou
confeſſeſt thy ſelfe) in beynge preſent and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
of them that offend agaynſt the ſeconde
table, and yet thou aſkeſt yf it be lawful to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
with thoſe that ſinne, (not agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſeconde table) but that worſte is, agaynſte the
fyrſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth it is, that they doe ſinne agaynſt the
fyrſt table through theyr ſuperſticion, &amp; impie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te
of their hartes,<note place="margin">and what is it that gydeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> but I doe not ſo, for aſmuch
as I do not communicate with them in harte &amp;
mynde, but only in body and outward ieſture.
But in the ſociete and felowſhip of adulterers
and theues, I cannot outwardly ioyne my ſelf
thereunto without ſinne:<note place="margin">who euer ſaw a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a hart co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to the Maſſe?</note> for then I ſhould do
agaynſt the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God, which
doe not onelye condemne the affections of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nynde, but alſo the outward facte of the body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:27"/>
                  <p>Wel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou groundeſt only al falſe ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſuperſticion &amp; impiete of the hart,
and that, which is onelye done outwardlye, is
no ſynne: and herein thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe to
be excuſed, in aſmuch as thou doeſt only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt
theſe thinges outwardly, without hauing
any reputacion or good opinion of the ſaid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyces,
and ſuppoſeſt that thou doeſt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte
Idolatrie with the Images of the dead
ſainctes, (in aſmuch as thou abhorreſt them in
thy hart) although thou do outwardly crouche
and knel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke ſo in dede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yf thou hadſt liued in the tyme
of Daniel, what other counſayl wouldeſt thou
haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the thre yong men, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, which
thou thinkeſt preſently to be lawfull? or els yf
thou hadſt bene in theyr place, wouldeſt thou
not haue done, as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt now? Thou wouldſt
haue obeyed the Kynges commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and
haue kneled downe with the reſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>No that I would not, for yf I had done ſo,
it had bene ſynne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore? Couldeſt thou not outwardlye
haue ſatiſfyed the Kynges commaundemente
by outward ieſture &amp; worſhipping, reſeruinge
alwayes vnto god the adoration and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
of thy hart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf I ſhould ſay: that they might outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
haue obeyed the Kynges commaundemente
with the reſt, I am afrayde to condemne thoſe
m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtyrs of God, that withoute anye neceſſitie
<pb facs="tcp:4739:27"/>
they dyd abandon theyr lyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s into daunger: &amp;
therfore it is better to confeſſe the trueth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou confeſſeſt then, that in all falſe ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of Idolatrye, they do not onely ſynne, that
beyng ſeduced through the errour of theyr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge,
conſente there vnto with theyr
hart, but all thoſe alſo that by outward ieſture
do communicate with them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe thy ſayinge to be trewe in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of the three young men, which thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeſt,
but not in my doynges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore?<note place="margin">It is all one, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adoratyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures is generally prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>For there it behoued them to worſhippe the
Image of a Panym and Heathen Prince: but
our worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (as diuers affirme) is another
kynde of adoration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>As touching that poynt we wyll debate the
ſame more amplye here afterwardes in tyme &amp;
place whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion ſhall better ſerue. But now
the queſtion is, yf that which thou doeſt, may
be excuſed, by that thou doeſt communicate at
the papiſticall ſeruyces, not with thy mynde,
but with the body onely. I haue gladly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
this thine excuſe, with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> example of thoſe
thre yong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to thend thou mighteſt perceyue
that thing not to be lawful, which thou ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
to be laweful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I am almoſt caught.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>What aunſwereſt thou to that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
ſayth:<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> the .xiiij. to the Romaynes: what
<pb facs="tcp:4739:28"/>
ſoeuer is not of fayth, the ſame is ſinne? Thou
canſt not in fayth be preſent and communicate
at thoſe ſeruyces which thou conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſt: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
all thy doynges therein is ſinne, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
doeſt not the ſame in fayth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe can I commnnicate in fayth at that
thing, which clearely repungneth agaynſt the
word of God, which is the onely ground and
foundation of fayth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſayeſt trewe: for vndoubtedlye thou
canſt not communicate in fayth at that thinge
which thy conſcience condemneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I condemne it truely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Then arte thou alſo condemned in aſmuche
as that thou doeſt, is not of fayth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Geue me the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that I my ſelfe
may ſee that texte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Holde, and reade it: it is in the ende of the
Chapter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Harken what the Apoſtle ſayth: Happy is
he that condemneth not him ſelf, in the thinge
which he alloweth, for he that maketh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
to eate, is damned yf he eate, becauſe he eateth
not of fayth: for whatſoeuer is not of fayth the
ſame is ſynne. In myne opinion, the Apoſtle
doeth not ſpeake here of vnlawful thinges, but
of thinges free and lawfull, to wyte of meates
which may be vſed with a ſafe conſcience. And
yf any do vſe the ſame agaynſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience in
that he thinketh not the facte lawful, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
condemneth hym ſelf, for aſmuch as he ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:4739:28"/>
not in fayth. But what ſerueth this to our
queſtion, which is not of indifferent and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
thinges, but of thoſe thinges that are of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſelfes vnlaweful? &amp; as for me, in my doynges
I do not condemne my ſelf although I do not
inwardly approue theſe papiſticall ſeruices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinketh that the obiection of Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſour
is ſomewhat pithy and ſtronge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth it is, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh there
but of thinges lawful and free. But for al that
conſidre (I pray thee) yf he be condmned that
doeth a lawfull and free thing without fayth,
becauſe he doeth not alowe theſame, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dmneth
it, and might for all that doe the ſame
withoute ſinne, yf he dyd alowe it, and dyd it
in fayth: what ſhall we ſaye of thoſe that doe
thinges, that are of them ſelues al together vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,
which alſo they condemne? In the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge
wherof they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue no fayth, for aſmuch
as they do not allowe the ſame. Yf a medecyne
that of it ſelfe is good, becometh hurtfull tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
the occaſion of hym that taketh it, what
woulde poyſon be to him, yf he receyued the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame?
For yf the medecyne euyll taken maye
anoye, how much more poyſon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe that there is poyſon in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall
ſeruices: but my ſoule toucheth it not,
but my body onely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:29"/>
                  <p>Lykewyſe he that vſeth lawefull and free
thinges euyll,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> receyueth them only with the
body, and not with the ſoule: for in that behalf
(that is to ſaye:) in ſpyryte, he doeth abhorre
them: and yet neuertheleſſe they conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trew becauſe they do condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſelues in theyr doynges: but as for me, I doe
not condemne my ſelfe in my doynges, neither
yet condemne my fact.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>This aunſwere woulde ſerue thee well, yf
our queſtion were of indifferent and lawefull
thinges. But for all that thou doeſt not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
thy ſelfe in the facte of vnlawful &amp; prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
thinges: thou art neuer the better thereby,
but worſe a great deale, then thoſe that beynge
blynded with erroure, do not condemne theyr
doynges: as peraduenture they would yf they
vnderſtode by the worde of God, aſmuche as
thou knoweſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf I knew this to be trew that you ſaye: I
woulde neuer be perſwaded to communicate
with them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet agayne I am caught, without knowing
any waye to eſcape. The ſaying of the Apoſtle
doeth conuince me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou canneſt not fynd a better waye to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape,
then to geue prayſe vnto the veritie, and
chaunge thyne opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What aunſwereſt thou
I pray thee vnto this generall ſentence: al that
is not of fayth is ſynne?<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> By this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is not
onely condemned all maner of eating without
fayth, but alſo generallye all that euer is done
<pb facs="tcp:4739:29"/>
without fayth. Where is now become your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour
communication and coniunction at the
papiſticall ſeruices, which thou and other thy
ſemblables do vſe, beyng ſo dyrecte contrarye
vnto the worde of God, as your owne conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
do teſtifye in condemning of the ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf this be trewe, ſuche people are in greate
daunger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>When I go to the papiſticall ſeruyces,<note place="margin">The cogi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion of diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers.</note> I
iudge it no great matterto diſſeble outwardli,
ſeynge I do reſerue faith perfectly in my hart.
I pray thee Euſebie, tel me, what ſemeth vnto
thee of this cogitacion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebie.</speaker>
                  <p>For the fyrſt part: Yf thou haue fayth in thy
harte, tell me, howe can the ſame be counſeled
and hyd? Thinkeſte thou that fayth is anydle
thing and without facte, and that ſhe maye be
ſo hyd in the harte, that ſhe cannot appeare out
wardly? Fayth is a fyre: it is impoſſible ether
to hide her, or incloſe her, but that ſhe wil ether
caſt forth flame or ſmoke.<note place="margin">Pſa. cxv.</note> The Prophete ſayth
and likewiſe the Apoſtle after him. I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued
and therfore haue I ſpoken. The fayth of
the harte is not dombe, but her violence brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
the barres of the mouth: for of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce
of the harte, the mouth ſpeaketh ſayth
Chriſt.<note place="margin">Math. xij</note> And the Apoſtle affyrmeth, that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
with the harte,<note place="margin">Roma. x.</note> iuſtifyeth: but to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
with the mouth, maketh a man ſafe. Take
away the confeſſion of the mouth, and then is
fayth dead. Wherefore take hede and beware
that thy diſſimulation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication with
<pb facs="tcp:4739:30"/>
the papiſtry, do not ſo thorowly hide thy faith
that it quenche not al together that litle ſparke
of fayth that is in thee. For as the fyre loueth &amp;
deſireth a freedom &amp; abundaunce of ayre, euen
ſo doth fayth deſyre to be knowen euery wher.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>And I feare the contrary. That yf I mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
my fayth vnto the wicked, that then it wyl
happen vnto me, as vnto thoſe that ſhow their
treaſure and money vnto theues.<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> And more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
Chriſte himſelfe doeth admoniſhe vs, that
we ſhould not caſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (that is holy) vnto dogges
and ſwyne, whereby I am perſwaded that it
is better to hyde priuelye this treaſure of faith
then that it ſhoulde be knowen of the wycked,
(who are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared vnto dogges &amp; ſwyne)
leaſt haply they do treade the ſame vnder their
feete, and deſtroy me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art then afrayde of thy fayth, as yf it
lay in the power of the wicked, to take it away
from thee. Trueth it is, that theues and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
may take away oure treaſure and ryches,
but the fayth which is in our hartes, cannot be
imbeſelled nor ſtollen, no, not of the gates of
hell.<note place="margin">Math. 16</note> The confeſſion of the mouth, cauſeth the
fayth (that is in the harte) to be knowen: but
it neyther deſtroyeth it, nor loſeth it, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
enterteyneth it, &amp; preſerueth it. For fayth
is of ſuche a nature, that yf it be not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated,
it periſheth: ſo much wanteth it that in
hydinge it, thou ſhalt preſerue it. Furthermore
is it not a greate follye of thee to thinke to
<pb facs="tcp:4739:30"/>
hyde thy fayth by diſſimulation: ſeynge that
for the ſpace of theſe twentie yeares thou haſt
alreadi inanifeſted the ſame to al people? Thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſte
thou that all thy neyghbours are ſo bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe
and ignoraunte that they doe not knowe,
that this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt, is no alteration of thine
opinion in religion, but rather a certayne diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation?
yea, and that not voluntarye, but by
violence and feare of the Maieſtrates? Thou
feareſt more this thinge, then the loſſe of thy
fayth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>In doyng the ſame (Euſebie) I do obey the
counſayl of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 10</note> who ſayeth: beware of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
for they ſhall delyuer you vp, &amp;c. As alſo, be
wyſe as ſerpentes, withoute omittinge of that
which I reſyted before: caſt not pearles before
dogges and ſwyne, leaſte they treade theſame
vnder theyr feete, and after retourne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
you. Thou knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thinges were
ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt, to his faythful flocke, to thende
they ſhould more diligentlye take hede to them
ſelfes. Wherfore I ſe not why I ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded
in keping ſecrete my preciouſe pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,
and in takinge hede to my ſelfe, leaſt I fall
into the handes of the wicked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I know well ynough the ſayinges of chriſt,
which thou haſt alledged for thy defence: wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
withall my harte that we all dyd knowe
the ſpyryte of Chriſt. Yf it be not tediouſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Temporiſour. I wyll declare vnto thee,
how thou doeſt abuſe thy ſelfe in the allegatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of theſe ſcriptures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:31"/>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>The houre is paſt, it is tyme to go home to
ſupper, one leſſe thou wylt Euſebie, reteyne vs
thy ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye ſee howe I am prepared to entertayne
my frendes, neuertheleſſe yf it pleaſe you to be
partaker of ſuche as God ſendeth (wyth me)
tarye. And I wyll forthwith cauſe ſome thing
to be prepared for ſupper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhall not nede Euſebie, that we ſhould ſo
many wayes moleſte thee, it hath ſuffiſed that
thou haſt paciently heard our fonde communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:
we thanke thee for thy good wyll. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe,
to thende I forget not my ſelfe, I
praye thee (yf to morowe thou haue no greater
affayres) that it would pleaſe thee to geue me
leaue to haue acceſſe vnto thee for an houre or
two, to ende our diſputacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Withal my hart, I am contented. Wherfore
yf it ſeme good vnto thee Temporiſour, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
we wyll mete in thy gardyne. And thou
Irenie yf it pleaſe thee, I pray thee be there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I am contente.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Although I ſerue nothing to further youre
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, yet God willing I wyl be ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Fare well then Euſebie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Fare well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>God be with you both.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>☞The ende of the ſecond Dialoge.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:31"/>
               <head>¶The thyrde
Dialoge.</head>
               <p>☞The Collocutours. The Temporiſour,
Euſebius, and Ireneus.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>IT behoueth me to go betymes to open
the gardyne, and tarye there to receyue
my frendes, as it apperteyneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinketh, the gardyne is opened, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
I haue taryed longeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Come in hether Irenie, haſte thou not ſene
Euſebius?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>No. I feared to haue come to late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou comeſt tymeynough:
how lykeſt thou this garden.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very pleaſaunte. Thinkeſte thou that,
that thou ſhalt not offend Euſebius with theſe
delectacions? for as farre as I can deſerne he
is nor the man that taketh any greate pleaſure
in theſe thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Ther is no dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, he knoweth wel ynough
this garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and furthermore as thou heardeſt,
he choſe this place, wherin we might come to
gether.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very wel: for it is my chefe deſyre, that
nothing be done, whereby any man may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended,
and therfore. I praye thee take in good
part, all that I haue ſayd vnto thee concerning
theſame. But ſee, he is here at hande, let vs go
to mere him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:33"/>
                  <p>This is my inciuilite to come ſo late. I ought
rather to haue taryed for them, and ſe they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
for me: but it goeth well ynough, for I ſee
them pleaſauntly diſpoſed. Geue vs grace (O
Chriſt) that we maye perfectely treate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
this queſtion: it is thy worke &amp; not myne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſte me great pleaſure Euſebie, in
coming hether. I feared leaſt ſome let or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
had happened vnto the, that thou couldeſt
not come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>There is nothing happened: but (that in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming)
I thoughte vpon our queſtion, in deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the ſame with my ſelf, wherby I came the
more ſlowely: Wherein (I praye you,) pardon
me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>You dyd well: and neuertheleſſe, we haue
not taryed long for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Chuſe whether ye wyll walke vnder thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
vy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, or ſyt downe at this table, to fyniſhe our
c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Seynge we are three, me thinketh it better
for vs to ſyt downe: to thende euery one maye
the better heare, and aunſwere: and alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone
more deliberately, the which thinge can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
ſo wel be done in walking. But yf your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
be to walke, I am contented.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue deuyſed the beſt waye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſo it ſemeth vnto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon me, although I beginne fyrſte: for
<pb facs="tcp:4739:33"/>
aſmuch as I haue promyſed to aunſwere vnto
the obiections of Temporiſour alledged out of
the .x. and .<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ej. Chapters of G. Mathew. Yf ſo
it be your pleaſures:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke it good Euſebie, in purſuynge thy
promiſe, that thou do proue vnto vs, whether
I haue alledged thoſe ſcriptures, well, or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll fyrſt declare, what is the trew ſence
of the wordes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the paſſage of S. Math. the. 7. cha.</note> and then we ſhall ſee
howe well to the purpoſe thou haſte alledged
them. It is playne that by dogges &amp; hogges,
he doeth meane, all carnall, fleſhely, cruell and
bloudthurſtye men: to whom in no reſpect ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayneth
holy thinges, nomore then pearles
to hogges. And therefore the Lorde wylleth,
that we do not wittingly manifeſt and declare
the ſecretes of his Kingdome to ſuche people,
confyaminge theſame by two pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>able argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
and reaſons. The one, for the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the worde and doctryne. And the other
for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the preachers &amp; teachers
of theſame word. Leaſt haplye (ſayth he) they
doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reade them vnder theyr feete, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourning
do deuoure you. That which he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
of treading vnder theyr feete, is meant of
the worde of God, but that which he rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
of tenring or deuouring, is meante of the
myniſters and preachers thereof. So that by
theſe wordes hys wyll is not, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
myſteries of the Kyngdomme of GOD
ſhoulde not be publyſſhed vnto the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:34"/>
or that we ſhould not freely and expreſſely con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe
the veryfie of the Goſpell of God before
the Maieſtrates when we are called therunto.
As haue done the Apoſtles &amp; an infynite nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre
of martyrs before vs. But rather, he doeth
adliyſe and perſwade vs by theſe ſayinges: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
it is not good nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient raſhely to declare
vnto wicked and carnall men, the miſteries of
the chriſtian fayth, whereby comenly enſueth
nothing els but contempt and deri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame,
with manifeſte daunger of theyr lyues.
And to theſame ende &amp; purpoſe he vſeth theſe
wordes in the .x. of S. Matheme. Beware of
men, and be wyſe as ſerpentes. Doeſt not thou
acknowledge and confeſſe, Temporiſour, that
this is the trew ſence &amp; meaning of the wordes
of Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot denye it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeenow then yf thou haue rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
alledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem for thy purpoſe, or no Chriſt
commaundeth that thou doe not throwe forth
they pearles before wicked and fleſhely people.
But he doeth not wyll thee ſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> them in
the ground, that the church neuer ſee them: for
thou thinkeſt that thou mayſt lawfully diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble
alwayes, before all maner of men, Further
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ore Chriſt doeth not thereby inhibite the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
of the veritie, but rather earneſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth
and requyreth the fame of euery chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and chefely when they are called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Maieſtrates. But thou, becouſe thou
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilte auoyde the daunger thereof, thou doeſte
not only diſſemble and hyd thy fayth, but that
<pb facs="tcp:4739:34"/>
worſt is, thou doeſt by diſſimulation contrary
to thy fayth and knowledge in communicating
at vnlawful ſeruice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> If this mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſcape
were lawful, then ſhould we haue no martyrs
in the Church of God, neyther yet any publike
confeſſion of the veritie of the Goſpel, ſo often
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded and practyſed by Chriſte and hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Apoſtles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>What is there then to be done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>What? That which thouſe eſt me do. I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hore
&amp; deteſt as a moſt ſtinking carrion, their
preſent eſtabliſhed religion, beyng wholy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
by the vngodly Biſhops through oure
demerites and ſumes. I abſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame
both in body and mynd, withall my famylie, &amp;
at home. I inſtructe my houſholde in the pure
doctryne of Chriſte and in his trew religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed
by his worde. And to this ende we
dayly reade at table the holye ſcriptures: &amp; the
better to confyrme and augment out fayth, we
ſinge certayne Pſalines &amp; holy ſonges. Euery
day we do reſyte amongeſt vs, the ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes
of almightye God: the Crede of the
Apoſtles, without forgettinge the mayer that
the Lord taught vs, to geue him thankes for al
his benefytes. This doe I dayly in my houſe.
And yet I go not through myne owne mocron
vnto the Maieſtrate, to declare vnto hym my
fayth, nor yet wittingly to caſt before dogges
and ſwyne, the holy thinges of God: but yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
caninduce any one into the waye of the truth,
or els reduce anye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſteayed out of the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:35"/>
I do it as dyligently &amp; as ſafely as I can. And
furthermore, I am alwayes readye to geue an
aunſwere of my fayth to eueryman, &amp; chefely
to the Maieſtrate, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I ſhalbe required ther
vnto, being wel contented to ſuffre &amp; indure al
that the Lord hath ordeined for me, in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.
This is a moſte ſimple &amp; chriſtian maner
of lyuing, not only to obey chriſt in his worde,
but alſo to kepe the conſcience pure, &amp; to geue
an aunſwere &amp; reaſon of the hope that is in vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I condemne nor blame not thy purpoſe and
doynges Euſebie, ſeyng thy fayth is ſuch, and
truely I would doe lykewyſe yf I dyd beleue
as thou doeſt. For although I do not agree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
you in opinion, yet I cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend and alow
any of thoſe that through feare doe diſſemble
in theyr religion, thereby not onely wounding
theyr owne conſcience, but alſo leadinge other
by theyr example into extreame daunger, the
which thinge myghte be eaſelyer remedied yf
they dydde proceade therein more gentlye and
humblye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I knowe well ynough Irenie, thy modeſte
and peaceable mynde, and therefore I was the
more deſyreous to bringe thee with me to this
collation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſte nowe, Temporiſour, my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owe I doe vſe my ſelfe and my famy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
in theſe troubleſome dayes, the whiche is
not onely myne, but alſo the example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:35"/>
&amp; of al thoſe that feare God, by whoſe
conuerſacion thou mayeſt eaſelye know what
thou oughteſt to do, and whether thou canneſt
defende thy facte by the wordes of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare it and vnderſtande it: I do alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
this conſtancye of thy mynde, the which
I would gladly imitate and folow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yf I were
not letted: for I declared vnto theem our fyrſt
collation what thinges impeached &amp; hindered
me in the attempting thereof. And I ſuppoſed
verely that I dyd not ſynne in communicating
with the body onely at the papiſtical ſeruices,
ſeyng that I dyd retayne alwayes in my harte
the veritie and trueth. Thou haſt as touchinge
this matter, alledged dyuers probable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
ſo that I ſee no way to replye agaynſt
the ſame. And chefely amongeſt other thinges
thou obiecteſt againſt me, that I do vſe a great
diſſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the which truely as yet, I do not
fele in my ſelf ſuch, as therby my doynges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
to be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. For I do not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate
at the papiſtical ſeruices, to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I would
ſeme to other to approue &amp; alowe theſame, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
I ſefe prayſe therby, or to abuſe or diſceyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by my preſence, but only becauſe that in
obeying the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Maieſtrates
I may auoyde al dan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. He truely ſemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
me properly a diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bler, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through his diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſeketh to abuſe al thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ether behold
him or heare him: in ſeking his own comodite,
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the detrement &amp; domage of other. But as for
me I do none of al theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to any ſuch end
<pb facs="tcp:4739:36"/>
I do not deſire to be reputed a papiſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
alſo that all people do know that Iowe
no good wyll vnto theyr relygion, ſo that the
Maieſtrate gather no matter agaynſte me of
rebellion, that is my onely care.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Hetherto thou haſt diligently laboured to
excuſe thy ſelfe, to thende thou wouldeſte not
be iudged a diſſembler, or abuſer of other ine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
but for all that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſt not eſcape, but that
thy outwarde facte is iudged of all me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for a
mere diſſimulation. For although thou doeſte
not ſeke to abuſe any man by thy diſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
yet for all that, thy outwarde facre beying diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable
from thy hart, (in cauſing outwardly
to appeare vnto the communicantes another
thing of thee, then the trueth is inwardlye) can
not, nor ought not to be reputed ſuche as it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
to be outwardly. And furthermore thou
art not certayne whether thou doeſt abuſe any
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or no, with thi outward preſence, for thoſe
that are aſſembled there w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the, euen as they be
ſimple and rude people, ſo do they thinke that
thy comming thither, is to the ſame iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
that theya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is. Thinkeſt thou, that thyne
opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thou hideſt ſo ſecretly, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
to euery one, ſo that thou doeſt abuſe no maner
of perſon in aſſiſtinge at the papiſticall ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
with the lyke ieſtur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and countenaunce as
they doe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>How can I abuſe any one of all my neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
ſeyng that it is euydently knowen vnto
them al, what fayth and zeale I haue had vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4739:36"/>
the Goſpell of God in deteſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
for the ſpace of .<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x. yeares paſte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea marye: yf dyuers of late had not onely
chaunged theyr outward maner of lyfe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
they: harte &amp; opinion: and are fallen ſo farre
that now they doe not onely condemne, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
ſharpelye perſecute that, which latelye they
dyd extoll vnto the heauens, I coulde redelye
name dyuers ſuch examples.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot denye it: I knowe ſome ſuche. But
I am of another opinion and mynde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleue the ſame: but tell me withoute fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
doeſt thou thinke that al men do certayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
know this thy mynde and opinion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I coulde be contented it were knowen: but
whether it be or no, I am not ſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſure thou canneſt not tell: my mynde
geueth me that Euſebius ſayth wel. For what
iudgement can I haue of any man, but only by
his preſent fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. To iudge after thinges paſte,
is no ſure iudgement, touching the doynges of
men, but moſt certayn of God, in aſmuch as he
is not mutable lyke vnto men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou vnderſtandeſt the thing wel, Ireuie:
and thou canſt not deuye it Temporiſour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreeſt thou then, that in aſſiſting at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall
<pb facs="tcp:4739:37"/>
ſeruices, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doeſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
in leadinge them ſo farre thereby that they doe
thinke thine opinion to be lyke vnto theyrs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it do differ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue ſayd it, and I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſay it: &amp;
that more is, I do not only confuſſe theſame to
be poſſible: but I doubt me greatlye, leaſt it ſo
happen vnto dyuers, my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtreayneth
me to confeſſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Tuſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Seyng thou vnderſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and eſt their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell me, yf
thou perceyueſt not alſo aſwell the great euyll
that thou doeſt to thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou abuſe ſte by
diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the great offence againſt God
and his church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I perceyue it not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Other men might make that aunſwere, that
feleth not the prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of conſcience, as doeth the
Temporiſour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll make thee vnderſtand and perceyue
what I meane Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poriſour, to thende that thou
knowing the ſame, mayſt amende it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>And I wyl geue dyligent eare thereunto.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſte of al, put the caſe, that I were one of
thoſe rude ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people, that nether vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode
the cauſe that is in diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nether ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
thy mynd in that behalf. Tel me (I pray the) in
the name of the liuing God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal ſe thee
at the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Idols, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ultar, at their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,
at their maſſes, in aſſiſtinge the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy
preſence at althoſe, in puttinge of thy cap, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; kneling downe with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what
<pb facs="tcp:4739:37"/>
other thing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can I thinke &amp; iudge of the, but
that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt likewyſe reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; worſhip thoſe
ſeruices, as I do? And what other thing doth
this thine exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple worke in me, but only a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
in myne errour, in w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawingine therby
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trueth of the goſpel? For I ſhall thinke
this w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſelf: what, behold yonder the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſour,
who hath ſo many yeres fauoured thys
new opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now ſuppreſſed &amp; ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
it cannot be choſen but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he knoweth al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
therof, &amp; yet ſe now he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
&amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerteth vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which truely he woulde
not do, yf he wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not thorowly perſwaded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
he was ſeduced &amp; abuſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new goſpel whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che
he lately profeſſed, &amp; now knoweth certain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew goſpel, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are the trew
church: god defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I ſhould forſake this
church and religion: yea, we ſhal wel perceyue
ſhortly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ſeduced wil come home
agayn to their mother holy church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which
thei haue ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſtraied. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre here, Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour,
what great occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of euil thou geueſt by
this thine exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vnto the ſimple &amp; ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>te
people, who haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> zeale of god, but not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to knowledge. For to what other end ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
theſe wordes of Ieſus Chriſte; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o thy
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Nota. Math. 18</note> wheras he ſaith: who ſoeuer doth
offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or cauſe to ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble one of theſe litle ones y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
beleue in me, it were better for him that a myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
were hanged aboute his necke, &amp; ſo to be
caſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea. For this thine exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
doth not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the blind papiſtes in
their errour, in hindring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therby to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4739:38"/>
knowledge of the trueth, but alſo that worſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
it doeth hinder and trouble the feyth of thoſe
little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who haue onely begon to beleue in
Chriſt, in putting them in daunger to retourne
to the papiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e agayne: ſo that by thyne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt of theyr fayth is hindered: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueſt
thou theſe thinges?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea: to much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I would to God that thou dyddeſt thorow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
perceyue it. Harken nowe wherin thou arte
offenſyue vnto the religion of God, and vnto
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the trew profeſſours and conſtant maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers
of theſame. Fyrſt of all, thou cauſeſt that
the wicked do ſo boldly ſpeake euyl of ſo good
a thing, in vtteringe innumerable reproches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the ſame, to thende it may ſeme the more
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dious and hateful vnto al people. Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte
thou not, that, the more the noumbre are
that conſente to vntrueth, (although it be but
by diſſumulation) ſo muche the greater is hys
power? And the more that vntrueth is mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned,
ſo much the more is veritie vilipended
and oppreſſed? Furthermore by thys meanes
the wicked become more importunate, bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſty
and cruell, agaynſt the trew religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
God to confound it, and all thoſe that wyl not
abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame. And ſo much the more cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
do they execute theyr tyranny vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
are conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as they ſe theyr noumbre increaſed
by thoſe that forſake the trueth. Theſe are Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour,
no newfound ymaginacions nor yet
vayne cogitacions, but the thing of it ſelf is to
<pb facs="tcp:4739:38"/>
notorious &amp; manyfeſt, by the dayly experience,
that we haue hereof. How canneſt thou no we
ymagine and thinke, that thou offendeſte and
hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſte nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by thyne example, when thou
doeſt anoye it moleſte all men thereby, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
papiſt, the weake chriſtian and me, and ſuche
other as I ami for this thy fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e tourneth alſo
to our great preiudice, in bringinge vs into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
daunger, becauſe we wyll not doe as
thou doeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>God defend that I ſhould be the cauſe of ſo
many great euyls.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare horrible thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not ſpeake in parables, but do playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
propoſe the thing, as it is to be conſydered.
And thou doeſt well, my frende Temporiſour,
to deſyre God to preſerue thee from beyng the
cauſe of ſo many euyls. But beware, leaſt thou
onely requyre theſame with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth, without
the conſent of thy harte, &amp; purpoſe to amende.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>As farre as I can perceyue, thou conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
me, to communicate no more at the papiſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call
ſeruyces, oneleſſe I wyll damne my ſelfe
wyllingly, and alſo miniſter greuous offences
vnto other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſo I do exhorte and counſay I thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>But I know dyuers that haue another ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of iudgement. Some hold opinion that yf
I wente not to theſe papiſticall aſſembles, I
ſhoulde myniſter occaſion of offence vnto the
weake &amp; ſimple. It is not me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e (ſaye they) that
<pb facs="tcp:4739:39"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e do gewe offence vnto the rude &amp; ignoraunt:
but it is an offence to contemne the common &amp;
ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine ſeruices. For the ſimple by this occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
do thinke euyl of vs, as mocker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
religion, exteming vs to be he rety<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes
of the Churche. Or at leaſte wyſe they
are prouoked by oure example to leaue theyr
publyke ſeruyces, whiche they as yet exteme
to be holy and lawefull, and in ſo doyng ſinne
agaynſt theyr conſciences. To thende therfore
that we doe not myniſter ſuche occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
we oughte to go to theyr ſeruyces, tyll
ſuche tyme as they are more playnelye inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
in the trueth of Gods worde, and doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon
theſame by theyr owne proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
as we haue done. Furthermore ſome doe
ſtaye them ſelues vpon the facte and example
of Naaman the Syrian, Nicodemus and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,
who were the ſecrete diſciples of Ieſus
Chriſt. Yf it were not greuous vnto the, Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie,
I would deſyre thee herein to heare thyne
aduyſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>It is eaſye to aunſwere vnto theyr dreames.
As touching the offence, which thou prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt,
It behoueth vs fyrſt of al to obſerue the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
betwixt the offence that is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without
any iuſt occaſion, and the offence that is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
whether it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or no: To know (I ſay) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
of theſe two is ſinne. The offence, taken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſtred, is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that any man is
offended w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that which of it ſelf is both good &amp;
lawful, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the facte is ſuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thereby thou
oughteſt rather to imitate the ſame, then to be
<pb facs="tcp:4739:39"/>
offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. And this is the offence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe
do alledge for their excuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
the papiſtes at their ſeruices, leſt haply the
ſimple &amp; ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people would be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded yf
ther did not come thither. But (I affyrme) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
that doth not come to theſe papiſtical ſeruices,
he doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is neceſſarely required to his
ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; worthy the zeale of a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And
this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple is ſuch, that it hindereth not: &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
ſome do find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes greued &amp; offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, it is theyr fault, &amp; procedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſelfes, &amp; not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the example geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for they may
not leaue the thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apperteyneth to their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
for any offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other may gather therby
For yf we ſhould leaue vndone al thoſe thiges,
wherof the wicked gather offence, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt we
bandon the pacience &amp; benignite of almightye
god, the which alſo the impenitent do abuſe to
their owne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. We muſt alſo laye a ſyde
the great liberalite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of houſhold, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned
of in the goſpel, who gaue aſmuch vnto
him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wrought but one houre in his vineyard,
as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued al the day, nothing regarding
the offence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wicked &amp; enuious perſons did
gather therof. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo accuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes,
Chriſte, the Apoſtles &amp; martyrs, becauſe they
did not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modate &amp; frame themſelues, to the
vulgare &amp; common doynges of other. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye
becauſe that the wicked maye gather no
offence: is it therfore lawful that the godly do
renounce and forſake the bountie of the deuine
maieſtie, in prouoking his indignacion againſt
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: were this expedient thinkeſt thou?
<pb facs="tcp:4739:40"/>
Wherefore yf I refrayne to damne my ſelfe,
with thoſe that reſiſte the trueth, and prouoke
the pacience of God, do I euyll? God forbyd.
Yf we maye not do euyll,<note place="margin">Roma. iij</note> that good may come
thereof, howe muche leſſe then oughte we to
doe euyll, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no goodnes can proceade there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
but rather much euyll: aſwell to them that
doe it, as to thoſe that ſee it? The offence that
is geuen, whether it be taken or no, is, when we
do any vnlawefull thinge, or els thoſe thinges
that are indifferent, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſo done that
they do offend the infyrme &amp; weake, for whoſe
ſake we ought to abſtaine, although otherwiſe
it lyeth in our powers to doe them, not onelye
voyde of ſinne, but alſo vnto edification. This
kynde of offence beyng geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is very haynous,
although noman be offended therewith: for yf
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oman be offended, that is rather to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
vnto the free conſcience of the beholders,
(who mighte yf they would, haue gathered an
offence thereof,) and not vnto him, that on his
behalfe dyd myniſtre the occaſion of offence:
vnderſtandeſt thou Temporiſour, thys diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
of offence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Verye well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Vnderſtandeſte thou alſo, whiche is euyll,
and which is not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Suffycyentlye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>You put me nowe in remembraunce of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:4739:40"/>
that are offended at the mariage of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,
but none are offended, that for the moſte
parte they are all geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vnto filthy whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
and common adulterye without al ſhame
leauinge dyuers deteſtable examples thereof,
by the which all degrees of people are greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
corrupted, and cauſeth the common tyttle of
oure Chriſtianite to be infamed and yll repo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of, euen amongeſt the infydelles. This is
the thinge, that alwayes hath greued me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſpeakeſte wel, Irenie. Is it mete, that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtian man fearinge GOD, do avſtrayne
from lawefull mariage, becauſe he would not
offende the ignoraunte: and in the meane tyme
polute him ſelfe wyth whoredome, the nexte
waye to depryue himſelfe from the Kyngdom
of GOD? What greater follye coulde there
be? Herein may ye beholde the excuſe of thoſe
that would haue vs go into the aſſemble of the
papiſtes at theyr ſuperſtitious ſeruyces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
we ſhould not offend the papiſtes: but
oure duery is, to doe directelye contrarye, as it
hath bene ſayde before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Hetherto Euſebie, thou haſte ſufficientlye
proued, that the excuſes (the which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged)
to auoyde offence, ſerueth nothinge to
this purpoſe. I woulde gladlye heare nowe
thyne aduyſe, as touchinge the examples of
Naaman, Ioſeph, and Nicodemus: for theſe
examples are alledged of all thoſe, that wyth
me do communicate at the papiſtical ſeruices,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:41"/>
onely with the body, and not with the ſpyryte,
and truely for my part when my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience dyd
accuſe me of my doynge in this behalfe, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
called to my remembraunce the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of theſe men, for the probation of my facte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>It is requyſite that theſe examples be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
wayed and conſidered, the which thing
cannot be forthwith accompliſhed: wherefore
myne aduiſe is that we do refarre the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll
oure next meting and collation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I am therewith very well contented, for I
haue nowe certayne buſynes that calleth me
home, that beyng done, I wyl retourne agayn:
when, and where, it ſhall pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Seyng you both haue thus determyned, I
wyl not gayne ſay it: but tell me Euſebie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
maye we come together agayne to fyniſhe and
ende this queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>To morow at this tyme, yf it pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I am contented. To morowe then, ye ſhall
fynd me (God willing) in this place at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre
appoynted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>The tyme, and the place, pleaſeth me well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke you both of your good wyll, yf e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
it lye in my facultie, the occaſion ſo myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring,
I wyll ſhowe you the lyke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:41"/>
                  <p>We do thanke thee that thou haſt vouch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
to call vs into this plea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nt place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll go before. Folowe you at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
God be with you both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>God kepe thee my frend, Irenie, we wyl
folowe thee by and by.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>☞The ende of the thyrde
Dialoge.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:42"/>
               <head>¶The fowrth
Dialoge.</head>
               <p>☞The Collocutours. The Temporiſour,
Euſebius, and Irenius.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>YF theſe examples of Nycodemus, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph
of Ara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thia, and Naaman the
Sirian, the which I, and my ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
are accuſtomed to vſe, do not bring
vnto me ſome preſent conſolation, I am
vtterly vanquiſhed and ouercome, I know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
no way to eſcape. I cannot tell, howe hereafter
wardes to excuſe my ſelfe, neyther towardes
God, nor my conſcience. And I doubt greatly
that they beyng narowly ſcanned and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
wyll lyttle ſerue for my purpoſe. For here
before when I began to vſe them for myne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
me thought alwayes they ſemed vnto me
to weake, to defend this my diſſimulacion: yet
we dyd alwayes alledge them agaynſte thoſe
that dydde reproue oure doynges, fearinge to
leaue oure wickedneſſe vncouered and naked.
This is the cuſtome of oure fleſhe,<note place="margin">The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the fleſhe.</note> for ſhe can
not abyde the reprofe of ſhame, althoughe ſhe
do both feele and knowe hyr nakednes, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
all poſſible meanes to couer the ſame. But
yonder me thinke I ſee comming both Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
and Ireneus. I am happy that I dyd acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
my ſelf with them, for they are both tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable
<pb facs="tcp:4739:42"/>
and gentle: and therefore I wyll not be
affrayde to purſew this matter both boldly &amp;
freely. What my frendes are ye come already?
I came but euen nowe hether to prepare thys
place for your comminge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>There neded no ſuch dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for the place
of it ſelf is very commodious and pleaſaunt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>That is trew. But herein I thought it good
to ſhow my good wyl towardes you. But thou
Euſebius, as farre as I can perceyue, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> comeſt
not vnarmed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo muche as hauinge about me a little
knyfe, neyther doe I prepare my ſelfe vnto the
warre, but vnto a louing and frendly collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet me thinke thou arte not withoute
weapons for the ſame, for eyther I doe abuſe
my ſelfe, or els the boke that thou haſte in thy
hande, is a ſworde of the ſpyryte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I vnderſtand what thou meaneſt Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour,
I was yeſterdaye lykewiſe armed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
theſame, although as then I had not this bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,
the which I haue now brought, therby the
more dyligently to examyne by the ſcriptures
the examples of Nycodemus, Ioſeph, and
Naaman the Syrian.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe weapons Ireneus, were more meter
for your Biſhoppes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which they haue
vſed of late yeres to murther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe of chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:43"/>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo, I cannot excuſe theyr doynges in
that behalf. I do often lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with my ſelf this
miſerable corrupcion &amp; alteracion of the eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
order, in beholdinge oure fleſhly Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
who ought to be ſpirituall Paſtours, to
become wolues in the ſtede of ſhepeherdes: &amp;
lyons and lyke vnto all other cruell kynde of
beaſtes, as theyr armes &amp; badges declare the
ſame. And where as they oughte to be ſeynge
biſhoppes, they are become ſo thorowly blynd
that they may be better called * Epiſcotes,<note place="margin">Epiſcoti, is aſmuch to ſaye as obſcured &amp; darkned</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi is as much to ſay as ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culatinge &amp; ſeynge Biſhops.</note> Epiſcopes: and wheras they oughte to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques,
they ar Cacolijcques, that is to ſay:
cruell or euyll wolues. In ſtede of eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
perſons, they are become ſeculer Princes,
and Lordes, and in ſtede of trew doctors, they
are become perfect troublers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>When we do reprehende theſe vyces wyth
innumerable other, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church
of Chriſt is deſtroyed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are we by thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes
condemned for heretikes, and iudged
to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre, but now tyme ſerueth not to bewayle
thoſe thinges, as alſo we ſhall profyte nothing
therin:<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> for ſalte ones beynge corrupted cannot
be reſtored to perfection agayne. The Lorde
wyll come ſhortely into iudgement, and reken
with thoſe wicked ſeruauntes to theyr eternal
damnacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Let vs refarre thoſe people vnto the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
<pb facs="tcp:4739:43"/>
of God: and yf it pleaſe thee, Euſebie,
I praye declare to what ende theſe examples
of Nicodemus, Ioſeph, and Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian
tende vnto: the which, not onely I my ſelf
but alſo all moſt all other doe alledge for their
excuſe, namelye thoſe that for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
of the hygher powers doe go vnto the
papiſticall ſeruices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I am right well content. But declare fyrſte
of al, howe you do alledge theſe examples for
your purpoſe and profyte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Wheras for feare of the wicked, we diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
our opinion touchinge the papiſticall reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
in communicating with them at the ſame:
we thinke we may lawfully doe it, and oughte
not therof to be reprehended as of an vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
fact: ſeyng that it is manyfeſt that the like
hath bene done by dyuerſe godlye men before
vs,<note place="margin">Iohn. iij.</note> as witneſſeth the Scriptures, who as we
rede,<note place="margin">Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> were neyther reproued nor condemned
therfore. Nicodemus was not ignoraunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
trueth, and he loued very well Ieſus Chriſte,
who alſo had him in good reputacion, and yet
all this notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, he fearing the Iewes
dyd diſſemble theſe thinges, neyther dyd he
withdrawe him ſelfe from the company of the
enemies of chriſt.<note place="margin">Iohn. xix. Ioſeph.</note> The lyke thing is mencioned
of Ioſeph of Aramathia, who as ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures
was a ſecret diſciple of Ieſus chriſt, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
for feare of the Iewes, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he liued.
It is lykewyſe ſpecifyed of Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Siria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:4739:44"/>
That the Prophete Elizeus dyd graunte hym
leaue,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 5. Naaman</note> that he beyng in the Temple of Remmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
before ſtraunge Goddes, for the aſſiſtaunce of
his Kyng, to knele downe, notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
by an excellent myracle, he was lately come to
the knowledge of one only trew God: yf theſe
men mighte then lyue ſo withoute offence, I
would gladly vnderſtand from thee, wherfore
theyr examples, doeth nothing helpe our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?
They kept theyr fayth ſecrete in their hart,
and outwardlye dyd communicate with thoſe
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they knew to be aduerſaryes to the truth.
They dyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al thinges like as we do now:
I meane, I and my ſemblables. Yf this diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
(as thou calleſt it) did not hinder their
ſaluation, wherefore then is it damnable vnto
vs? is God chaunged, in condemning now, the
thing that he before ſuffred in his children? I
thinke it not to be trewe. For euen as he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
one, and immutable, euen ſo cannot his
determinacion chaunge more at one tyme, then
at another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou reaſoneſt ſtrongely, Temporiſour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou thinkeſt ſo: but haue a lyttle pacience
and thou ſhalt iudge otherwyſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Myne argumentes are ſuche Euſebie, as
dyuers doe thinke them very ſtronge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe that they are pleaſaunte vnto the
ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>efull fleſhe, therefore do ye gredelye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb facs="tcp:4739:44"/>
them, and deſire more that they might be
fyrme and ſtronge, then that ye thinke them ſo
in dede. For eyther I am greatly abuſed, or els
ye do wittingly deceyue your ſelues. But now
let vs come to youre argumentes, and to begin
withall, I do admoniſhe you of one thing: that
is, that all thoſe that vſe to alledge theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
for theyr excuſe, are not in one lyke ſtate
and condicion, although they do acknowledge
theſame trueth that we doe. With the harte ye
loue the goſpel of God, but outwardly ye com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municate
with the papiſtes: hytherto ye agree
together, but on the other ſide there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
for ſome of you haue publykely renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
the papiſme, and haue theſe certaine yeres
freely approued the doctryne of the Goſpel, as
I, and other haue done. But nowe temptacion
beyng come, they leaue the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelike churches
and retourne to the papiſme and papiſtrye, to
thende they may lyue the more without daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
in this world: and thou arte Temporiſour,
one of this company. The other ſort, although
in theyr hart they acknowledge the trueth,<note place="margin">Inglande cannot pleat this excuſe.</note> yet
dyd they neuer publykely confeſſe the ſame nor
maynteyne it, neyther yet renounced the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
communication with the papiſtes, but
ſtyll perſeuer in theſame hytherto, of whiche
ſorte there is in the world no ſmall noumbre: &amp;
namely in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Almany. Who is he that
doeth not now perceyue the great difference y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
is betwixt theſe two ſortes of people, and that
to no purpoſe, they doe both alledge for them
ſelues the examples of Nycodemus, Ioſeph,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:45"/>
and Naaman the Syrian? And fyrſte, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge
thee, Temporiſour, and thoſe that are
lyke vnto thee: who haue preſently forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
trew religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The trew Image of Ingland.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ye haue publikely mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned,
and are now reuoulted &amp; tourned back<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde
into theſame myre and puddle, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
which ſometyme ye were yſſewed out, &amp; dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.
Truelye theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of Nicodemus &amp;
of the other two, do nothing ſerue for your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
nether do ye in any reſpecte imitate theyr
doynges. For yf theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples might ſerue for
the defence of any diſſimulacion, yet ſhould it
not ſerue for your ſyde: but rather for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
other party. Who, as they did neuer publikely
profeſſe the goſpell, ſo can they not be accuſed
of any reuoulting or renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing in that behalf.
The thing is apparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Nicodemus &amp; Ioſeph dyd diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble
theyr fayth for feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, they were
but newly come vnto this doctrine, hauing the
ſame onely inwardly incered in theyr hartes,
without ether as yet forſakinge the iudeiſme,
or els publikely ioyning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the fayth
ful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt. What lyke thing find
they now here in the example of theſe two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
wherby thei may iuſtely excuſe their doinges:
thoſe (I ſaye) that of late dyd publykelye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouche
the Goſpell and are nowe reuoulted
from theſame, in tourninge to the papiſticall
ſuperſticions, as dogges vnto theyr vomete?
And that which I haue ſpoken of Nicodemus
and Ioſeph maye alſo be veryfyed of Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
the Syrian. Who beynge a Panim was
<pb facs="tcp:4739:45"/>
newly come vnto the knowledge of God, with
out euer beynge vnited vnto the ſociete of the
people of God and theyr religion: yea, he was
altogether newe and younge in his fayth and
in the knowledge of god, who had healed him.
Conſydre now I praye you, howe much thys
his example ſerueth to couer the facte of oure
diſſembling Chriſtians: who not onely for the
ſpace of many yeares haue bene perfectely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
in the trueth, by ſincere doctryne, but
alſo vnyted and knytte vnto the ſame by holye
Sacramentes purely myniſtred? Is ther any
apperaunce or lykelyhode herein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>As farre as I perceyue by thy communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
they defende them ſelues very poorely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I harken, and vnderſtande all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray thee my frend Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poriſour, tel me by
thi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. In the beginning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou didſt
tourne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the papiſme, dydſt thou neuer call
to thy remembraunce theſe examples? werre
thou not then as ingenious and wytty to ſowe
figge leaues together to couer thy ſelf, as thou
art nowe? And wherefore? for (thou ſayeſt) it
was not then nedefull: for the reuoultinge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the papiſme, required no ſuch defence and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueringe.
But nowe yf ye mighte retourne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
to the papiſme withoute ſynne by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
communicacion, contentynge youre
ſelfes to beleue onelye wythe the harte, ye
mighte more iuſtelye haue remayned in the
<pb facs="tcp:4739:46"/>
papiſme withoute forſaking theſame,<note place="margin">A greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſme, and now ioine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ther vnto agayne.</note> in reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
your fayth ſecretely in your hart, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
might ye haue defended then youre diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
by theſe examples, as ye do now. Who
compelled you to forſake your auncient religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
Truely the feare wherewith preſentlye ye
are aſtonied, doth moue ye more to retourne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
to the ſuperſticions ones forſaken, then
dyd at the firſt, the charitie and deſyre of vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
moue you to come to the trueth: in aſmuche as
agaynſt your conſcience ye are nowe declyned
agayne to your former communicacion, of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticions
and falſe ſeruices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe then are not culpable, that haue not
as yet forſaken the outward ſociete and felow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip
of the papiſtes, although they haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding
of the trueth, but do perſeuer ſtyll in
this communicacion, the which not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
they do not allow in theyr hartes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaye not ſo Temporiſour: But rather by
this communicacion do labore to admoniſhe
you, how vnaptly ye do applye to your behofe
theſe examples of Nycodemus and Ioſeph.<note place="margin">Ingliſhe diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers can not iuſtly alledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Nycode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus for theyr ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</note>
As touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Nicodemiſtes herein they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
from you, that although they be not voyde
of ſinne, yet (I ſuppoſe,) that they doe not
ſynne ſo greuouſly as ye doe. Wherfore to the
ende ye may more playnely perceyue that your
facte ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be excuſed by theſe examples. I wil
leaue you, and examyne the cauſe of thoſe that
more iuſtly may be called Nicodemiſtes, then
<pb facs="tcp:4739:46"/>
you. Who, yf they cannot be excuſed by theſe
examples, as it ſhall notably appeare: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may
we eaſely deſerne and iudge how litle theſame
ſerueth for your defence. For yf theyr doynges
be damnable, &amp; can fynde none excuſe by theſe
examples, there is no man ſo voyde of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
that doeth not eaſelye perceyue, that
much leſſe is your facte excuſable, and cannot
be compared to the examples of Nicodemus,
Ioſeph, and Naaman the Sirian.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceyue well to what ende thou preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
Euſebie. Thou ſhalt do me great pleaſure
to examine this matter narowly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Let vs fyrſt conſydre the doynges of Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus
and Ioſeph.<note place="margin">Where to tende the examples of Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus &amp; Ioſeph.</note> In theſe examples there
is ſomethinge to be reprehended, ſomethinge
to be excuſed, and ſomethinge to be prayſed
and commended. This thing is to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,
that they fearing the Iewes, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
God, durſt not confeſſe the trueth which they
dyd know, and durſt not ioyne them ſelues to
Chriſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt his faythful flocke, but hiding
almoſt theyr fayth, dyd yet communicate with
the enemies of Chriſt. Confeſſeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> this poynt
Temporiſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea: proceade.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>This thing in their doynges was excuſable:
that the ſeruyces whereat they dyd communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
were not the ordinaunces of men, but of
<pb facs="tcp:4739:47"/>
God, and therefore not vtterly to be diſpyſed
as thinges odious and ſuperſticious, and all
though the tyme dyd approche wherein they
ſhould be aboliſhed: yet, as then it was not ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſted
&amp; openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but remayned ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured
&amp; hyd, that many yeares after the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of the goſpel, the multitude of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were yet deteyned vnder theſe
legall obſeruacions, as it playnely appeareth
in the boke of the Actes the .xi. Chap. Thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeſt
to theſe thinges alſo Temporiſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot gayne ſaye it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Fyrſt of al then, this thing in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
prayſe, for that in theyr hartes they dyd ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue
and allowe the veritie, which other prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces
dyd impunge and condemne: furthermore
alſo for that they dyd not conſent and agre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
the Phariſeis in theyr Sinagoges, conſulting
agaynſt Chriſt, but dyd withſtande theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
to the vttermoſt of theyr powers.
As S. Luke mencioneth of Ioſeph of Arama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia
in his .xxiij. Chap. and S. Iohan of Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus
in his .vij. Chapter. Thyrdely when as
the maieſtie and glorie of the goſpell of God,
ſemed to the outward appearaunce to be vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
ſubdued and ouerthrowen: to wyte, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as
Chriſt was crucified &amp; dead, &amp; his Apoſtles,
the one hauing betrayed him, the other denied
him, and the reſt forſaken him, al this not with
ſtanding, theſe worthy perſons w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of diſſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boldly declare both
<pb facs="tcp:4739:47"/>
to Pilate, &amp; to the highe Preſtes &amp; Phariſeis,
theyr fayth &amp; confidence, in him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had
crucifyed by the begging of his body, &amp; bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
theſame ſo honorablye as was poſſible,
Canſt thou impunge, or haſte thou any thinge
to replye againſt theſe thinges, Temporiſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing at all. But do meruayle greately,
where about thou goeſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>That is eaſye to be perceyued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Harken, and I wyl tel thee whether I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende:
we haue peruſed and conſydered what
it is of the example of Nicodemus &amp; Ioſeph,
wherby dyuers thinke to couer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of theyr religion,<note place="margin">Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtes.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wyl call Nicodemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,
becauſe it ſhall not nede often to vſe anye
circumlocucion. This example conteyneth thre
thinges. The firſt is, reprehenſible, the ſecond
excuſable, and the thyrd commendable. Now
I demaund of thee Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poriſour, which of theſe
thinkeſt thou, that a man fearing God, oughte
to folowe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>The aunſwere is ready: to wyte, the thyrd,
the which euery chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harte acknowledgeth
to be onely commendable, both before God &amp;
man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou aunſwereſt well. For to this end ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
all examples, namelye, to ſtyre vp in vs a
certayne imitacion and folowing. But we may
not imitate and folowe theſe thinges that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
are of them ſelues, nor yet cannot bee
<pb facs="tcp:4739:48"/>
in vs commendable and prayſe worthye. And
therfore it behoueth vs to vſe a great diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
in folowing the examples of Saynctes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerne
betwene the doynges that are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable,
and thoſe that are vyciouſe &amp; culpable:
hauinge nede of pardon by the grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of God in Ieſu Chriſt. For it were a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous
&amp; pernitious imitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a Publicane
ſhould alledge for his excuſe the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of S.
Mathew: or an adulterer, the example of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:
a reuoulter and denyer of the truth, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of S. Peter: or a dronkarde the dronke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of Noah, for to couer theyr ſynnes by the
examples and dedes of the Sayntes. Why ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
doe they not folowe the conuerſion of S.
Mathew, the great repentaunce of Dauid and
Peter, &amp; ſobriete of Noah? But let vs ſe what
thing the Nicodemiſtes do folowe in the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Nicodemus, and for what purpoſe they
doe alledge theſame. Truely they doe it for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
els, but thereby to excuſe theyr facte: but
that thing nedeth no excuſe, that deſerueth no
blame, but is worthy prayſe: as when they doe
receyue into theyr hartes, with them, the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of Chriſte, the whiche the Princes of thys
world do ſo extremely perſecute, and do not by
any meanes agree and conſent with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
&amp; ſuppreſſe theſame. But herein they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
theyr excuſe, in that they fearing me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more
then God, do not vnitie and ioyne them ſelues
publikely to the truth, according to theyr faith
and knowledge, in renouncing and forſakinge
the papiſticall ſeruyces, which they condemne
<pb facs="tcp:4739:48"/>
in theyr hartes: but by a wicked diſſimulation
do communicate at theſame agaynſt theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.
And for to excuſe this theyr ſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
they do alledge the examples of Nicodemus &amp;
Ioſeph, not in that thinge, that they dyd wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
prayſe, but in that thing, wherin they ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
namely in theyr diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and feare of
man. As yf the ſynnes of the Sayntes, mighte
ſerue to excuſe oures. Vnderſtandeſt thou Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreeſt thou alſo there vnto?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely I do not allowe thoſe, that doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
alledge for examples the thing that is wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked,
then that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable: but for all
that I thinke it cannot be denyed, but that we
may excuſe the infirmitie of our fayth, by the
infirmitie of the Sayntes, without being iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
and condemned for wicked, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they:
or as people hauing renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced the knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
becauſe we dare not publykelye confeſſe
theſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou acknowledgeſt and confeſſeſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmitie
of fayth that reſteth in the Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtes:
but now is it mete &amp; conuenient I pray
the, that weakelinges, do alledge the infirmite
of the Sayntes, therby to excuſe theyr ſynne &amp;
infyrmitie? or rather oughte they not to accuſe
them ſelues, and with plentie of teares and all
humilitie to haue recourſe vnto the throne of
<pb facs="tcp:4739:49"/>
grace, thereby to obtayne remiſſion of theyr
ſinnes, and confirmacion of fayth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy reaſon is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, Euſebie, I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye
agaynſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Irenie.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely Euſebie, I do not heare theſe thinges
vnwillingly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebie.</speaker>
                  <p>Lette vs conſydre furthermore thys one
thing: that Nicodemus and Ioſeph dyd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
at the ſeruyces and ceremonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
lawe, according vnto the commaundemente of
God: in the which ſeruyces there was no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piete,
ſuperſticion nor falſyte: but the Nicode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſtes
of our tyme, do communicate at the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtrye,
beyng full of the falſe ſeruyces of the
ſayntes departed, of Aungelles and of Idols,
with an infinite noumbre of other ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
that dayly prouoke vnto wrath the longe
pacience and benignitie of almightie GOD.
Wherefore I praye thee Temporiſour, what
agreement is there thinkeſt thou, betwene the
doynges of Nichodemus and Ioſeph, &amp; oure
counterfeyte Nicodemiſtes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>In myne opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, none at all, for I perceyue
now wel ynough, the greate difference that is
betwene them. But for all that dyuerſe men,
(therby the better to couer theyr fact) do apply
the thing that is worthye reprehenſion in the
papiſtical ſeruices vnto a good vſe, ſayinge: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
the principall effecte thereof is dyrected vnto
God, and to his ſonne Chriſte. And although
there be dyuers humayne inuencions to much
<pb facs="tcp:4739:49"/>
ſuperſticiouſli added thereunto, yet for al that
the trew and perfect ſeruice remayneth whole
and ſound.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe maye that be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Paraduenture, Irenius can tell thee better
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I: for I neuer had them as yet in ſuch eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion
as I thought them worthy, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
to memorye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſmuch as I can remembre, I wyll reſyte.
Fyrſt of al they ſaye,<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall baptiſme</note> and affyrme that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall
baptiſme maye be ſupported as it is
miniſtred, becauſe that the ſubſtaunce of the
ſame: to wyte, the worde and the water remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth,
notwithſtandinge the ſuperſticions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexing
thereunto of oyle, ſpittle, creame, ſalte,
candle, cryſome, and exorcyſme: not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
alſo the latyne interrogations after the
ſymbole of the Apoſtles, and the ignoraunte
au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſweres of the witneſſes or god fathers there
preſent in the behalf of the chylde, beynge all
together done in a foreyne language not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded
of the aſſyſtaunces. As tonchinge
the Maſſe,<note place="margin">the maſſe</note> they ſaye that they maye go there
vnto without ſynne, for although it be reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
with diuerſe ſuperſticious ceremonies
inuented by the biſhops: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge
it doth ſtyl retayne the principall effecte of the
inſtitucion of Chriſt: to wyte, the Sacrament
of the bodye and bloude of the Lord. As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
Idols, they au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere,<note place="margin">Of ydols</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they paſſe not
<pb facs="tcp:4739:50"/>
of the Images of wood, of ſtone, of golde, nor
of ſiluer. The which they knowe well ynough,
by the worde of God, ought not to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped:
neyther are they ſet vp, to be ſerued &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured,
but onely to helpe the memorie, to the
ende that the laye and ignoraunt people maye
be prouoked by the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſayntes,
to imitate theyr liues.<note place="margin">Of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge.</note> As touching their chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and ſinging, they lytle paſſe and regarde,
wherfore or to what end the papiſtes do ſing:
for they in the meane tyme do pray vnto God,
according to theyr fayth in commending them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues
vnto him. This is almoſt the effect of al
that euer thy alledge for theyr excuſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf it were not for the preſent queſtion that
I haue to au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere, I would Ireneus, examine
theſe theyr particular excuſes, and proue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly,
that they in ſo doyng, doe ſynne more
greuouſly then any other. But thou Tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour,
knoweſt thou not that theſe theyr excuſes
are moſt deteſtable and wicked?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe. I know the ſame to be moſt trew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Another tyme, the lyke occaſion beyng my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred,
I wyll declare my iudgemente in that
behalfe.<note place="margin">It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſari for vs to knowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che we do communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate.</note> In the meane tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre a lytle this
one thinge. Theſe fooles paſſe nothinge at al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
with what Church they do communicate, ney<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther
with what Prelates, and Preſtes they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
aſſociate them ſelues, at theyr deuyne ſeruices<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
They thinke it ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4739:50"/>
thereof, although the appendaunces annexed
thereunto be manifeſtly wicked. For whereto
ſerueth all theyr ceremonies in theyr Temple,
but onelye to ſeduce theyr auditore, in makinge
them lyke vnto themſelfes: to wytte, ſimoniac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,
fornicatours, ydle bellies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>koffers, and
ſlaughterme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ſhepe of Chriſt, beyng
condemned by theyr owne decrees, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
heareth the maſſe of ſuch a one, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth
moſt abhominable and greuous ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie,
nether do they paſſe any thing at all of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
which is ſpoken by the mouth of the prophete.
I haue hated the congregation of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
Neyther wyll I ſytte downe with the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.
But let vs leaue them there, and retourne
to our matter. I praye thee now Temporiſour
tell me, is this example of Nicodemus &amp; Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph
ſufficiently examined, or deſireſt thou yet
to know any other thing therein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Nomore, for this preſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Lette vs come nowe then to the example of
Naaman the Syrian.<note place="margin">Naaman</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>We thinke our ſelues to haue herein a great
ſtaye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Let vs conſydre now, whether it ſerueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
thing for your purpoſe, or no. Let vs ſe the
ſtorye which is in the .iiij. boke of the Kinges,
the .v. Chapter. This example is alſo partelye
commendable, partely excuſable, and partelye
<pb facs="tcp:4739:51"/>
reprehenſible: it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, in that he doth
not attribute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of his myraculous hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of his leproſye, nether vnto the water, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
vnto Eliſeus: but vnto the onelye God of
Iſrael. And furthermore he dyd immediatlye
acknowledge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that there was none
other God, but the God of Iſrael: by this con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion
reprouing all other Goddes, as vayne
and falſe. And thyrdly in that he proteſted and
purpoſed to do no more ſacrifice vnto none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Goddes, but onely vnto the Lorde, in vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
renouncing the ſuperſticious ſeruyces of
al ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goddes, the which he had ſerued in
tyme paſt, in aſmuch as he was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were no Goddes, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes
of mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Theſe are his doynges, where
in he is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended &amp; prayſed, beſyde that
he dyd not ſhowe him ſelfe ingrate &amp; vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
towardes the Prophete. This is excuſable
in his fact, in that he requyreth to haue the bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then
of two moylles, of the earth of Iſrael, for
to make an aulter, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which he mighte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
vnto the god of Iſrael. God truly hath
no regarde vnto thoſe thinges. But in aſmuch
as in that tyme the people ſerued God by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
ſacrifyces, thys good man knewe not
howe to ſhowe forth hys fayth and newe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
of hys harte, then by doyng ſo as he ſaw
it requyſyte amongeſte the Iſraelytes. But
thys is reprehenſible,<note place="margin">Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de this ſo farre, as that he could not dwel and ſerue him ther, with out offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde.</note> that he hauing acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
and confeſſed one onely trewe GOD,
dyd not forthwith withdrawe hym ſelfe, from
the courte and ſeruyce of hys King and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter:
but (remayning ſtyl in hys eſtate) dyd his
<pb facs="tcp:4739:51"/>
accuſtomed ſeruyce towardes the Kyng: yea,
and that namelye in the Temple, where as
ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Goddes were worſhypped, the which
aboue all other thinge he oughte to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted
and abhorred, conſyderinge hys for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
proteſtacion and promyſe. This faulte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
he hym ſelfe acknowledged and confeſſed
in hys facte. For marke what he ſayd vnto the
Prophete. There is one thing, for the which I
deſyre thee to praye the LORDE for thy
ſeruaunte, that when my mayſter goeth into
the Temple of Remmon for to worſhippe, and
he leaninge vpon myne arme, yf I doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe
alſo, that the LORDE wyll be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull
vnto his ſeruaunt, becauſe of this thing.
Theſe wordes declare euydentlye, that he dyd
knowe, that he coulde not wythoute offence,
from thence forthe bowe hys knee in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Remmon: no, not for the ſeruyce of the
Kynge hys mayſter, in aſmuche as he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted
before to worſhyppe none other, but
the one onely trew GOD of Iſrael: and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
he deſyred the Prophete, that he woulde
praye to God for him. He did not as then tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly
purpoſe and determyne wyth him ſelfe
to doe ſo:<note place="margin">Nota.</note> that is, to worſhyppe in the Temple,
but fearinge, leaſte he ſhoulde not be ſuffered
to exempte hym ſelfe from hys offyce, he ſayd
not, I wyll worſhyppe: but, yf I doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe
in the Temple of Remmon, that is to
ſaye: yf I cannot relinquiſſhe and forſake
myne offyce. Alſo I vnderſtande thys ſeruice
of hys to bee an inclynacion and ſubmiſſion
<pb facs="tcp:4739:52"/>
that he vſed towardes the Kinge, and not a ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce
that he purpoſed to doe vnto ſtraunge
Goddes: which thing is eaſye to be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
by the circumſtaunce of the text, for he did
not ſaye abſolutely, yf I do worſhip in the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Remmon: but, when that my Lorde the
Kyng doeth entre for to worſhip, etc. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
worde, which we call (worſhippe) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth
properlye, to inclyne and bowe the knee.
This good faythful man had now no deſyre to
worſhip any more the God Remmon, but for
aſmuche as he knew that it was not ſufficient,
to abſtayne onelye from the worſhippinge of
ſtraunge Goddes in his harte, oneleſſe he dyd
alſo abſtayne from all outwarde appearaunce
of adoration; therefore he aſketh pardon of the
ſame, praying that the Lorde would diſpence
with him in his facte. Theſe thinges are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
in this hyſtorie, that euery one that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
it, doeth forthwith perceyue it, excepte it
be the Nicodemiſtes. Now I pray thee, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour,
what thing is there herein that maye
ſerue for thy defence, and other thy felowes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>This thing truely maketh for vs, in that, all
though he did acknowledge the trew God, yet
neuertheleſſe, he fearing to offend his Kynge,
dyd accordinge to his accuſtomed maner, (all
though it were nowe agaynſte his wyll) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
in the Temple of Remmon in aſſiſting at
vnlawfull ſeruyces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>But that is not certaynly knowen whether
<pb facs="tcp:4739:52"/>
he dyd ſo, or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For he ſayd: yf I worſhip in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Temple of Remmon. And yet ye conclude that
he dyd as welworſhip after his conuerſion as
he dyd before: what maner of conſequence is
this? (becauſe he ſay dyf I do worſhip) therby
to conclude that he dyd worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I admyt
he dyd worſhippe: yet were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible:
the which, as I haue declared before,
yt ought not to alledge any example of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible
facte of any Saync<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, to imitate &amp;
folow theſame. And yf ye wyl all gates be the
folowers of the thing that is reprehenſible, at
leaſt wayes ioyne this alſo therunto, (pray ye
the Lord to pardon youre diſſimulacion,) but
ye cannot doe that, oneleſſe fyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te of all ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
the faulte, and then ſorowe earneſtlye in
repentaunce: but this laſt part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hindereth you
greatly to aſke pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for ye your ſelfes know
that ye ought not to hope for pardon of anye
ſynne, with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t repentinge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and yf ye
dyd vnfaynedly repent it then would ye inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
your ſelues to leaue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>We extem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this fault (yf at leaſtwyſe there
be any) to be very lighte and tollerable, and to
be amongeſt the nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of the ſynnes, that are
called veniall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye do then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> your ſynnes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
ye cannot all together couer them.<note place="margin">we ought not to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer oure offences.</note> But howe
much better were it to waye them a litle more,
to the ende ye mighte the rather be occaſioned
thereby to leaue your faultes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd more ſurely
<pb facs="tcp:4739:53"/>
obtayne pardon for the ſame? It is not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie
of a noble and faythfull harte, to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
nuate and mitigate his owne faultes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>But the Prophete him ſelf dyd not make ſo
much a doe aboute this matter, as I perceyue
thou doeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Open the boke, and reade therein, what au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
he made vnto him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll reade it. The texte ſayth thus, (vnto
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid: Go in peace.) What thing gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
thou hereof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>What? That the Prophete dyd not iudge,
that Naaman ſhould ſynne, yf for the fauoure
of his mayſter he dyd worſhyp in the Temple
of Remmon, orels that his ſynne was ſo ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
and venial, that God would eaſelye pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>This is your expoſicion, becauſe it pleaſeth
you beſt, in aſmuch as it ſemeth to permit your
ſinnes to remayne vnpuniſhed. But I pray the
my frende Temporiſour, what did this Syria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
demaund of the Prophete?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>That he would pray vnto the Lord for him
that he would pardon him, yf euer he did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp
in the Temple of Remmon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>What aunſwered the Prophete?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:53"/>
                  <p>Thou hardeſt it euen now. Go (ſayd he) in
peace: the which wordes importe a plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſoth, to that which he demaunded.
He aunſwereth not concerninge the pardon,
which is only in the handes of God, but onely
concerning his prayer: to were, that he would
praye vnto the Lord for him, according to hys
requeſte. So that we cannot hereby conclude,
that ſuch kynd of worſhipping ſhould be voyd
of ſinne. The which thing, yf it had bene trew,
aſſure your ſelfe, the Prophete would playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
haue tolde him theſame, to thende that he
ſhould make no conſcience of ſynne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, where
in there was no ſynne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>In this poynt I agree with thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſeeſte then, that there is ſynne, in ſo
doyng.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> eſtemeſt it to be ſuch, as the lord wyll
eaſely pardon the ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſo ſemeth to ſignifye the conſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Prophete.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>It behoueth vs diligentelye to conſydre
in the perſonne of this Syrian, certayne cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces
and cauſes, (which diffre great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you,) which alſo moued the Prophet to
accord ſo eaſely vnto him his demaund, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
him to departe in peace. The which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your diſſimulacion, although
you do alledge this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple neuer ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
to couer your ſynful ypocriſie withall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:54"/>
                  <speaker>☞Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>Which are they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue touched them partelye here before.
Fyrſt he was a ſtraunger, a Syrian, a Panim,
and one that was in high eſtate &amp; greate repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion
with his Kynge and countrey,<note place="margin">A compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Naaman and oure Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſours.</note> &amp; newly
come to the acknowledge of God: yea, he was
a new and tender plant in the fayth of one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
trew God, and was not as yet vnyted and
ioyned with the people of God by any Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
wherby he could not, nor ought not to
be burthened w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great &amp; wayghtye thinges,
as thoſe that were more ſtronger and perfect:
beyng inſtructed and noriſhed of long tyme in
the trew fayth amongeſte the people of God.
Furthermore he dyd proteſte and ſweare that
he would neuer ſerue more any ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Gods,
but the onelye God of Iſraell: in teſtimonye
wherof, he toke the burthen of two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>oylles, of
the earth of that laud, for to make therwith an
aulter vnto the God of Iſrael: the which thing
the Prophete would not a permitted and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
an Iſraelit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to haue done, in aſmuche as
it was not lawfull for a Iewe to ſacrifice vnto
God in any other place, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he had
appointed and choſen. Wherfore as vnto a Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
&amp; not vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iſraelite: he permitted vnto
him that thing, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h he would not haue gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
vnto an Iſraelite. For the Prophete exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d
it a greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rdnes in the Syrian, that
in condemning all other ſtraunge Goddes, he
had acknowledged &amp; confeſſed the onely trewe
<pb facs="tcp:4739:54"/>
god of Iſrael, in proteſting to ſerue him only.
It was not (I ſaye) withoute a cauſe that the
Prophete dyd ſo greatlye exteme theſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges
in the conuerſion of a Panim. And that
as touching the reſte, he did ſo well incourage
him, promyſing to demaund of God pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for
him. I pray thee Temporiſour, what wouldeſt
thou do, yf that ſome great Lorde out of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kye,
for the lyke occaſion came hyther amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt
vs: and he, by ſome lyke myracle beyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the chriſtian faythe, and to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledginge
and confeſſinge of one onelye Ieſus
Chriſte, the onely ſonne of God, and onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer
of mankynde: and then would proteſt &amp;
ſweare, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence forth he woulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
the Mahometicall religion as falſe, &amp; cleue
vnto the onely religion of Chriſte. And yet not
withſtanding, would requyre that it might be
pardoned hym, yf at any tyme through the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of his office, he dyd come with his prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce
vnto the Temple of Mahomet, and there he
leaning vpon his arme ſhould alſo be conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
to knele downe with him? What thing (I
ſay) wouldeſt thou doe in this caſe? wouldeſt
thou not aunſwere the ſelf ſame thing that the
Prophete here aunſwereth vnto the requeſt of
the Syrian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon me, Temporiſour, in that I ſpeake
my conſcience. Truely thou ſhouldeſt doe very
foliſhlye and vngentillye yf thou dyddeſt not
aunſwere euen as the Prophete dyd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4739:55"/>
                  <p>Verely I would aunſwere euen ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>But now conſydre on the otherſyd, yf ther
be any reaſon of excuſe for a Chriſtian: that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
he hath longe tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
of Chriſt, &amp; beyng perfectely inſtructed
in the knowledge of the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, &amp; of
the grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel, would require the ſame
to be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto him, that the Prophet hath
permitted vnto this ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Syrian, and that
thou lykewyſe wouldeſt permit vnto the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhe
Lord, after thou hadſt wayed the circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
of the cauſe and perſon? Thinkeſt thou
that your ſinne is to be compared vnto the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie
and frayltie of Naaman the Syrian?
Doeſt thou not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre this ſentence: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
much is geuen, much of him ſhalbe requyred?
What man is ſo farre depriued of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
that wyll requyre aſmuch of a chylde, as
of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? or of a young plant, as of an old tree?
Euen ſo truely, hath piete and godlynes their
increaſinges &amp; growinges: for we doe a greate
deale more eaſelye ſupporte the infyrmitie of
thoſe that are beginners, then the remiſſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
of thoſe that are, or ought to be further
inſtructed. What ſayeſt thou here vnto, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I agree vnto all that thou ſayeſt: I am van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhed
and ouercome by the manyfeſt trueth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Doeſt thou acknowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that theſe Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemiſtes
haue nothing now in the examples
of Nicodemus, Ioſeph, &amp; Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Syria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4739:55"/>
to couer theyr ypocriſie withall, but contrarye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe,
that the infyrme &amp; new fayth of theſe i .ij
is a greate deale greater &amp; more better, then is
theyrs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I do acknowledge it, &amp; cannot withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me then, yf that thoſe whiche haue not
as yet outwardely renounced the papiſme (all
though that in theyr harte they do fauour &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
the goſpel, yet for al that they haue not as
yet publikeli co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed theſame) yf thoſe (I ſay)
do not fynd in theſe examples any thing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
theyr diſſimulacion, as before I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?
how then canſt thou and thy ſemblables,
who haue of long tyme publykely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed the
Goſpell, and renounced the papiſme, couer or
defend by theſe examples youre great ypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye
in declyning from the trueth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe vnfaynedly, that there is nothing
in theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples that maketh for oure purpoſe,
in aſmuch as our cauſe is waightier the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs:
ſo much the leſſe then, do theſe examples ſerue
vs, then them. But tell me, what ſhall I doe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou aſteſt of me? did I not ſhow
thee before?<note place="margin">The laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e counſayl.</note> My counſayl is that thou doe as
thou ſeeſt me do. I admoniſhe the in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of
Ieſus chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſearche nomore excuſes for
thy ſinnes: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thy fante, and forſaking
the ſociete of all vnlawefull and ſuperſticious
ſeruyces, ioyne thy ſelfe wyth thoſe that
walke dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ectely in the trew religion of Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:4739:56"/>
Praye alſo the Lorde to pardon thy tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
in that thou haſte abuſed by thyne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
thy weake brethren, offended the ſtronger,
and confyrmed the ydolater in his ydolatrye.
Thou haſt hereof many notable examples, for
to appeace and aſſure thy conſcience agaynſte
all the barkinges of the wicked and vngodlye:
which ſhall ſerue thee for thy better confyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
then thoſe abuſed examples that thou haſt
hytherto alledged. Folowe rather the example
of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, and dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
godli men, that haue alwaies by outward
fact declared the inward fayth of theyr harte:
and dyd not as yet make any ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwen
the interiour and exteriour communicacion in
religion. Why rather doeſt not thou allow and
folowe the example of Tobias in the which is
no reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Tobias.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which hyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou
haſt alledged to couer thy ſynnes withall? To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias,
although he was the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be
and lynage, and although the Iewes of the .xij
Tribes went to the golde Calues of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
he fled from al theyr companies, and went vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Ieruſalem, vnto the Temple of the Lorde,
wheras he dyd worſhip (according to the law)
the Lorde God of Iſraell. Thoſe whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye
he auoyded, were alſo Iſraely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es aſwel
as he, and dyd boaſt of the trew God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; of his
trew ſeruice, aſwel as he, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning al thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
that for to ſerue the Lord, woulde go to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,
(in aſmuch as the Lorde was no accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of perſones nor places.) I praye thee Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſour,
tell me, why dyddeſt thou not aſwell
<pb facs="tcp:4739:56"/>
choſe this example, wherin there is no vice nor
thing worthye of reprehenſion (but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended
by the ſcriptures) aſwel as the other?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it that thou enquyreſt, Euſebie?
the aunſwere is readye. Nicodemus, Ioſeph,
and Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd pleaſe vs better, becauſe that
theyr exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples ſemed better to agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the eaſe
of oure fleſhe, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in a more world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſecuritie, then the example of Tobias.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>For aſmuch now, as thou vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt that
poynt ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. Tell me what doeſt thou fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
hence forth purpoſe to do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I purpoſe by Goddes grace to withdrawe
my ſelfe from all Ipocriſye and ſuperſticion,
vnto the confeſſion of the trueth, &amp; for aſmuch
as this determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is mixte with many dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:
I moſt inſtantly deſyre the Lord to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
and forgeue me myne offences paſte: as
alſo that he wyll vouchſafe from hence forth
to fortyfye my fayth agaynſt all the aſſaultes
of the deuyll.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lorde confyrme thee in this thy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe:
That agayne at the fyrſte brunt thou doe
not recule backe and geue place vnto the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
as one vtterly diſmayed and aſtonied. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre
alwayes the thinge that I dyd admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe
thee of in our fyrſt collacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to wyte, that
thou do in tyme withdraw thy ſelfe from this
diſſimulacion: otherwyſe thou art in daunger
<pb facs="tcp:4739:57"/>
to loſe the pricke of thy conſcience, that doeth
as yet continually admoniſhe thee, &amp; ſo to fall
into an obſtinate blyndneſſe,<note place="margin">We muſt in time w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>draw our ſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al papiſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by lyfe or by exile and flighte, yf we wyl a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperacion the end of diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion.</note> and hardneſſe of
harte, &amp; finallye into deſperacion. For I praye
thee Temporiſour (conſydre dyligentlye with
thy ſelf) what other thing can they attend and
loke for, that beyng ſo vtterly abaſhed &amp; afraid
at the threateninges of a miſerable &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
man, do agaynſt theyr owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
at vnlawfull ſeruyces: but that alſo
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuyl ſhal aſſault them more greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and cruelly, they muſt nedes be ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
blynded, and brought into extreme deſperaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
Thou knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fall of the<note n="*" place="margin">Hofmai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter the munke in germany. Frauncis Spera in Italy. Mayſter Hayles in Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are the ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Goddes iuſtice vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to althoſe that do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinge agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimoni of theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</note> Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke Hof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayſter,
in this land of Germanie: &amp; of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
Spera in Italie, who are the greate admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicions
of God, to thoſe nacions, to be vygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
in the worke of the Lord, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant in fayth,
pacient in afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by no meanes agaynſt
theyr conſciences to denye the truth. Happy is
he, that can be warned by other mennes daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I geue thee hartie thankes of this thy great
diligence vſed towardes me. In that thou haſt
vouchſaued to preſerue &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> draw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolf, a poore ſtrayed ſhepe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>For aſmuch as thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is ſuch Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour,
I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not geue the beter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterly
to deuide &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> draw thy ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our aſſembles,
tyl ſuch tyme as thou wayſt vnderſtand more
playnly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therein is nothinge contayned that
may hindre thy ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I do cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl
thee, ſo would I do my ſelf, yf I were ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb facs="tcp:4739:57"/>
as thou art.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſt Irenie, as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a modeſte &amp;
mylde nature. I would to the lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou didſt
thorowly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
I wil not refuſe at any tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhal pleaſe
the, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>farre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the in this behalf, to thy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
edificacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the Euſebie, as yet I do not greatly
fantaſye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter: but yf hereafter at any time
my hart be inclined thereunto, I wyll not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
thy great modeſtie &amp; fidelite, but ſo muche
the rather deſyre thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poriſour.</speaker>
                  <p>My frende Euſebie, for aſmuche as by the
prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, I am by thy meanes indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
to relinquiſhe &amp; forſake al pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtry, I pray
thee do not leaue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come &amp; viſite me at my
houſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to aſſiſt myne infirmite with
ſome comfortable Scripture of the grace of
Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll doe it gladly. The Lorde confyrme
thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>His peace, make an ende of all this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſye,
that ſo much troubleth the church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen ſo be it. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The peace of chriſt
is not of this worlde, ſhe is not voyde of the
verytie of GOD, ſhe defendeth no errours,
ſuperſticions, falſe ſeruyces nor any other exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable
ſynnes, nor yet the Tyrannye of falſe
Chriſtians, but contrarywyſe ſhe doeth paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye
the conſciences of the faythfull towardes
GOD, and then amongeſt them ſelues. The
ſame peace my frende, Irenie, make the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4739:58"/>
a trew and perfect Irenie, that is to ſay, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
and a louer of peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>☞Ireneus.</speaker>
                  <p>I deſyre it withall my harte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Temporiſour.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke ye both, that it hath pleaſed you to
aſſemble here, at myne inſtance. I offer you
my ſeruyce, and commende my ſelfe vnto your
prayers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶Euſebius.</speaker>
                  <p>Let vs praye God, one for another, I wyll
go home to my houſe, you maye folow when it
ſhall pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>☞The ende of the fowrth and laſt
Dialoge.</trailer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>☞Pſalm. xxvi.</bibl>
                     <p>I haue not dwelt with vayne perſons: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
wil I haue felowſhip with the diſceytful.</p>
                     <p>I haue hated the congregacion of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked:
and wyll not ſyt among the vngodly.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶An excellent
admonicion and reſolucion, of the godlye and
famous learned man Celius ſecundus Curio.
Dedicated vnto all faythful Chriſtians, to the
ende, they (beyng warned) may auoyde al
ſuperſticious and erronious papiſticall
ſeruices. Tranſlated out of Frenche
into Engliſh. By R. P.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>☞Pſalm. xvi.</bibl>
                  <p>¶Al my delyte is vpon the ſainctes that are in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he earth, &amp; vpon ſuch as excell in vertue. But
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey that runne after another God, ſhall haue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reat trouble.</p>
                  <p>Theyr drinke offering of bloud wil not I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,
nether make mencion of their names with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n
my lippes. The Lorde him ſelf is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion
of mine inheritaunce, and of my cuppe: he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hall maynteyne my lotte.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>¶Iob. viij.</bibl>
                  <p>¶May a ruſhe be grene without moyſtnes?
or maye the graſſe growe withoute water? no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut (or euer it be ſhot forthe, &amp; or euer it be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hered)
it wythereth before anye other herbe.
Euen ſo goeth it withal them that forget god,
and euen thus alſo ſhall the ypocrites hope,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome to nought. His co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe deſtroied
and his truſt ſhalbe a ſpyders web. He ſhall
leane vpon his houſe, but it ſhal not ſtand.
He ſhal hold him faſt by it, yet ſhal
it not endure.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4739:59"/>
            <head>¶An excellent
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dmonicion and reſolucion, of the godlye and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amous learned man Celius ſecundus Curio.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edicated vnto all faythful Chriſtians, to the
ende, they (beyng warned) may auoyde al
ſuperſticious and erronious papiſticall
ſeruices. Tranſlated out of Frenche
into Engliſh. By R. P.</head>
            <p>THe brethren beyng as yet in Babilon,
doe aſke oure aduyſe: to wytte, yf it be
not lawefull, and conſonnant wyth the
worde of God, in a pure conſcience, to
be corporally preſent, to aſſiſte, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
at the Babilonicall papiſticall ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es,
the harte beyng abſent and alienated from
all ſuperſticion and vayne religion. To whom
fyrſt of al, I aunſwere: that it is harde to geue
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail to thoſe that are oppreſſed with ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
tyrannie. In aſmuche as on the one ſyde,
theyr great calamitie doth inclyne the harte to
pytie and compaſſion: and on the other ſyde,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eritie doeth reuoke the ſame to himſelfe. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
in determining, the mynde is led hyther &amp; thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
into dyuerſe ambigio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and doubtful co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitacions.
For I my ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to fore
experimented the lyke payne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, haue
learned for the loue of thoſe that are as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
in the ſame, to leade my lyfe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
and heauihes. Albeit, notwithstandinge
<pb facs="tcp:4739:60"/>
that the har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cannot refrayne it ſelf from ſuch
affections: yet neuertheleſſe it behoueth vs to
trauayl, that this our counſayl &amp; aduyſe be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al harted, amitie, angre, pitie
and from al ſuch affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as cuſtomably doth
reuoke the mynde from the veritie and trueth.
Wherfore I beſeche theſe my moſt deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
to pardon me, yf in geuinge counſayle I
ſhal ſpeake any thing that ſhal ſeme ouer harde
vnto them, not hauing accommodated my ſelf
ſufficientelye to theyr infirmitie: but rather to
perſwade them ſelfes, that not onely by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayl,
but alſo by ayde and fact, we would moſt
gladly in all poſſyble maner ſupport theyr ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this deliberat determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
we wyl propone and ſet forth two endes to the
which all oure doynges are to be refar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed.</p>
            <p>The one is the glory of the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and the righteouſnes of the ſame. The other is
the ſaluacion of oure brethren, that is to ſaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the Church: Where vpon fyrſt of all, I wil ſay
this much. That yf we had perfectely learned
Chriſt,<note place="margin">i. Corin. i.</note> and had onelye knowen him to be our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſanctificacion, righteouſnes, &amp; redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.
Yf we had (I ſay) accumelated &amp; heaped
vp, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ryches &amp; treaſure in heauen, wheras h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
is ſet downe on the right hand of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
we ſhould haue now no nede of theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſes
and conſideracions. For then we ſhould
know that our duety is to abandon al worldl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
thinges for his ſake:<note place="margin">Math. x</note> as fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ryche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luk. xiiij</note> &amp; alſo our owne lyues to the ende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
reſerue, kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and entertayne in al fayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:60"/>
fulneſſe, the pure &amp; perfecte ſeruyce of Chriſt,
and the religion, honour, glory and maieſtie of
his name. And furthermore we woulde ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
oure ſelues by all poſſible meanes not to
offende oure brethren, neyther by fact, worde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
nor diſſimulacion: for whom Chriſt Ieſus o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
Lord hath vouchſaued to ſuffre death: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in imitatinge his example we ought to be
preſte and ready to ſhed our bloud for them, in
confyrming them in the trueth.</p>
            <p>The fyrſte thinge then, that it behoueth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
chefely to attempt, is thorowly and perfectely
to learne Chriſte, and to waxe ryche in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
knowledge of hys name: from whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nelye procedeth the fyrmyte and conſtancye
of the mynde. For whereas ſome doe perſecute
Chriſt in hys membres, ſome doe denye hym
before the Maieſtrates, and other ſome doe
diſſemble theyr fayth in hym: From what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thinge doeth this proceade (ſuppoſe we)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut onelye of ignoraunce, and wante of the
knowledge of chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe ar vtterly voyd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
knowledge of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that doe perſecute him:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or yf they had knowen hym,<note place="margin">i. Corin. ij</note> they woulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er
haue crucyfyed the Lorde of glorye. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le
doe they knowe hym, that eyther doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye
hym: or els do diſſemble theyr knowledge
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they haue of him. For as much as ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſimulacion is a certayne kynde of denyall.
For yf they had thorowly learned Chriſt, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad bene perfectely inſtructed in the doctryne
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Goſpell, yf they had at any tyme recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ite of Chriſt, and had taſted of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the celeſtiall grace: none of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4739:61"/>
thinges ſhould haue happened vnto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but
rather (as it is ſaid of the apoſtles) thei would
haue witneſſed Chriſt with great confydence,<note place="margin">Actu. 4. 9 and. 10.</note>
in ſettinge aparte all other thinges, and haue
maynteyned his trew ſeruyce and pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
with a merueylous conſtancie. Let thoſe that
thinke it lawful to ſemble or diſſemble in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
tell me, where appeareth in them the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
of Chriſt? Where is the ſaluacion &amp; exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of theyr brethren: by the which they ought
to indure and bringe them to Chriſte? As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the glory of God, it ſhineth not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt
them: in aſmuch as by theyr ſylence and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacion,
they doe not onely obſcure it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
aſmuche as in them lyeth they doe vtterlye
quenche it. On the other ſide, how do thei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
the ſaluacion of theyr brethren, conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
that by theyr pernicious example they do
wounde theyr conſciences, and confyrme them
in all ſuperſticion, and falſe religion? and yet
notwithſtandinge, they knowe Chriſt to haue
ſayd:<note place="margin">Math. x.</note> he that confeſſeth me before men, I wyll
alſo confeſſe him before my father and his au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels:
And he that wyl not confeſſe &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
me before men, but denye me, I wyl not
alſo acknowledge him, but denye hym before
my father. And as touching theyr brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they
are not ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the greuous threateninges
of the Lord vnto all thoſe that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offende one<note place="margin">Math. 18</note>
of the leaſt of thoſe litle ones that truſt in him
They are not ignoraunt alſo,<note place="margin">i. Corin. 8</note> of that which his
Apoſtle Paul hath ſayd:<note place="margin">Galat. ij.</note> that all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſynne
agaynſte theyr brethren, in woundinge theyr
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ake conſciences, doe ſynne agaynſt Chriſte.
<pb facs="tcp:4739:61"/>
Where is it that the holy ſcriptures doeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
any diſſimulacion in religion, and holy
thinges: Or rather wher is it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? Let ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s call to theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce,
&amp; diligently conſydre the excellent
example of the thre worthy younge Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Danie. iij</note>
that in time paſt in Babilon (vpon the lyfe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
miniſtred) dyd ſeriouſlye debate this
queſtion, in making a notable diffinicion and
reſolacion of the ſame, worthy of all men to be
imitated and folowed. Did they in any reſpect
diſſemble? or rather dyd they not thinke it me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to expoſe them ſelues quick vnto the flamy
fornace,<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> then to inclyne to any diſſimulacion?
But the ſoule and mynd (ſay they) aby deth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
firmely fixed in God, although the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
do diſſemble in outward facte, at the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
ſeruices, (this do they alledge:) But let
them aunſwere me:<note place="margin">Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere.</note> hath not God created and
geuen, aſwell the bodye as the ſoule: Hath he
not reſerned and dedicated them bothe vnto
him ſelfe? Ought we not to beleue with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart
vnto iuſtificacion?<note place="margin">Roma. 10</note> and with the mouth and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
exieriour ieſtures, oughte we not to make
confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The wyfe in abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
hyr body to the vſe of another man, ſhall
ſhe be excuſed towardes hyr huſbande, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
that ſhe hath alwayes reſerued him moſt
deareſt in her harte? no truely. And as this is
no reaſonable excuſe, euen ſo is not the other:
but rather much leſſe to be alowed. Thou whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
art but one, wilt thou deuyde thy ſelfe? in
dedicating the one part of thee, vnto Chriſt: &amp;
the other to Antechriſte? Wo worth this dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4739:62"/>
and cowardnes of mynd, wherin reſteth
ſuch peruerſite, that eyther for feare or for any
other cauſe do declyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our dutyes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyces,
which I owe vnto the immortall God:
we (I ſay) whoſe parte it were to ſuffre al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of death for mortal men. But they replye,
ſaying:<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> That for a ſinguler commodotie &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte
vnto the church of God: or for a good end
and purpoſe, it is ſometyme lawfull to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
I aunſwere that there is no greater como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie
then to obſerue the trew and perfect reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:<note place="margin">Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere.</note>
there is no comodite more greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
glorie of Chriſt, and the ſaluacion of oure bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.
For we may in no wyſe do euyl,<note place="margin">Roma. iij</note> how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
ſoeuer it be (as witneſſeth S. Paule) to the
ende that good may come thereof: nether hath
God any nede of our lyes, and diſſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.
It ſemeth that the Apoſtles haue ſometyme
diſſembled, but in very dede they dyd not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble,
but vnfaynedly for a time thei did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
that which was conteyned in the law, to
the ende that by that meanes they might alure
and winne the Iewes vnto the knowledge of
Chriſt: wherin they dyd nothing againſt their
conſciences, for aſmuch as the ceremonies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vſed were firſt eſtabliſhed by the word of god.
But we contrary wyſe, nothing regarding the
premyſes, do thoſe thinges not onely, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
of God, but alſo vehemently reproued
by his holy word.<note place="margin">Math. 28</note> And fyrſt, as touchinge the
forme &amp; order of Baptiſme, the which the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical
preſtes do now vſe, although it be true
that the ſame be auayleable and effectual vnto
young childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng baptyſed therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
prophenacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cannot anoye: yet
<pb facs="tcp:4739:62"/>
not withſtanding vnto the aged, &amp; vnto thoſe
that are ſufficiently inſtructed by the word of
God of the impiete of the ſame, it is vnto them
nothing els, but the marke &amp; token of the Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonicall
armye, whereby they ioyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues
vnto Antechriſt, &amp; proteſte to ſerue him in hys
warres.<note place="margin">Luke. xxij</note> Yf any queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
aulter,<note place="margin">i. Corin. 11</note> to the which the people ones in the yere
at leaſt, do runne ſo faſt? what other thinge is
it, but a general monſterday, of the garriſon &amp;
ſouldiors of Anthechriſt?<note place="margin">Ebre. ix.</note> Yf any do aſke oure
aduyſe of the maſſe? what other aunſwere can
we rendre, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the great enſigne &amp; ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dart
of Antechriſt, eleuated and erected vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Chriſt &amp; his merites, vnder the which al
the ſoldiours of Antichriſt doe aſſemble them
ſelues:<note place="margin">Canti. iij. Danie. iij</note> or els it is the great Image of gold ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
by Nabuchodonoſor, to the dedicacion &amp;
worſhipping wherof al the Babilonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble
&amp; come together: the which alſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywyſe
al the Iſraelites of God doe flee &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre.
Yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſke our aduyſe of theyr Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall
howres,<note place="margin">Collo. iij.</note> of theyr latyn Mattens and
Euenſong, and of theyr ſolemne ſinginge and
Ceremonies? We aunſwere that they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
els,<note place="margin">Danie. iij apo. 17. 18</note> but the tabrettes, harpes, vyalles &amp;
ſwete armonye of the Kynge of Babilon, and
the pleaſaunte daunſinge and melodye of the
roſe coulered whore attired in purple. Yf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye
doe doubte,<note place="margin">Deute. v.</note> of the worſhyppinge of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles,
and of the inuocation of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Saynctes,<note place="margin">Iohn. iiij</note> we certyfye them that it is no
thinge els but a battayle and ſtryfe,<note place="margin">i. Cori. xij</note> wherein
we do openly fight agaynſt God &amp; his chriſt.<note place="margin">Eſay. 28.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:63"/>
Finally yf any doe diſpute of the funeralles &amp;
ſeruyces of the dead?<note place="margin">Mat. viij</note> we affyrme it is nothing
els,<note place="margin">i. Teſſa. 4</note> then vnfortunately to periſhe in battayle,
in makinge compoſicion with death and hell:
thereby renouncinge lyfe and heauen (that is
to ſaye:) Chriſte hym ſelfe, in buryinge oure
ſelfes wyth the wicked in vngodlines. O how
miſerable are we, yf we acknowledge not theſe
thinges: and more miſerable yf we know them
and do diſſemble them: and moſt miſerable yf
we do allowe them, and openly defend them.
Yf the brethren do conſydre theſe thinges, and
dyligentely examyne the ſame, they ſhal eaſely
knowe, to what ende all thinges oughte to be
refarred, and in what maner it behoueth them
to lyue. For yf they do not ſet before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes
certayne determinate endes, where vnto they
purpoſe to dyrecte all theyr doynges and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylles:
then of force they muſte nedes ſtraye
from the right way. Wherfore as we ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
there are two endes ſet forth vnto euerye
Chriſtian man. The fyrſt: the ſekinge of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement
of the glorye of God. The ſecond:
the wealth and ſaluacion of our brethren, as a
thing annexed vnto the fyrſt. Now, in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>much
as we are obliged vnto Chriſt, and do marche
vnder his ſtandart: it behoueth vs by all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
meanes to ſeke the auauncement of hys
glorye, and that with the haſarde of oure ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
and ſmarte of oure bodyes: oneleſſe we
wylbe reputed traytours to hys Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>But for aſmuch as dyuers are ſo infyrme &amp;
weake, and indewed with ſo lyttle knowledge
and fayth, that they dare not publykelye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
<pb facs="tcp:4739:63"/>
and forſake the ſuperſticio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
I woulde counſayle ſuche not to attempte or
enterpryſe any thing raſhely: but to kepe them
ſelues within in the lymities of theyr fayth, with
out forſaking theyr vocacion, tyll ſuch tyme as
they are growen vp into a more perfection,
knowledge, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. Let ſuch (I ſay) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the reading of the holy ſcriptures
in theyr houſes. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diligently repaire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
ſuch as haue the gyft of interpretacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are
of godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let them ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes pray
vnto God the father of our Lord Ieſus chriſt,
that he wyl increaſe theyr fayth, ſo that at the
laſt they may grow vp into perfect me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
ſuch as becometh the trewe diſciples of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt. And yf at any tyme, ether frayltie,
or feare of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or any other thing, do cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
to withdraw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this their purpoſed
determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating with the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
at theyr wicked ſeruices &amp; execrable ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries:
let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware that thei doe not by any
meanes excuſe their fact &amp; doynges: but rather
accuſe &amp; condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, &amp; that before god
and theyr brethren, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by theyr euyl example
they haue offended. In bewayling their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
ſeruitude &amp; wante of ſtrength,<note place="margin">i. Corin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to reſiſte
temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Aſking pardon of the Lorde, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes wholy to the mercy of God,
to the ende (that they beyng voyde of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl,
what to doe;) it may pleaſe the Lorde to geue
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch hartes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant mindes rather to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
death for the glory of his name (yf nede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre)
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continually to lyue in vnquietneſſe
of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences poluted with ſinneful Idolatrie,
<pb facs="tcp:4739:64"/>
Or els yf it pleaſe him not to geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great
a gyft, &amp; frute of faith (which is geuen but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
few) that then he wyl vouchſafe to ſhow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the meanes &amp; way, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thei may eſcape
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great tyrannie, in ſeruing the Lorde in a
pure &amp; fre religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in a quiet &amp; peaceable place.
The which thing truely, our good celeſtiall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
wyl performe: and wyl not ſuffre vs to be
aſſaulted aboue our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth: but wil acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhe
the good deſyre of his ſaynctes, in ſatiſfyinge
thoſe that thyrſt after righteouſneſſe. We haue
by the aſſiſtaunce of God his ſpirit, produced
this litle admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the conſolacion of our
brethren, beyng as yet in the Babilonicall cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie,
amongeſte the papiſtes: for aſmuch as
we were informed that they required oure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe
herein. Wherfore yf they deſyre to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
inſtructed of any thing els by vs: as are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
declaration of the places that ſome are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med
to alledge out of the holy ſcriptures, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
defence of theyr diſſimulacion: or els the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of thoſe thinges that are more ingeniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y,
then faithfully of diuers excogitated &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.
Or els yf there be any that (not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented
with this my writing) deſyre farther to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
&amp; ſatiſfyed: let ſuch reade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writinges
and iudgementes, of ſuch learned &amp; vertuouſe
brethren, as haue moſte purely and ſincerelye
intreated of thoſe matters: whoſe wrytinge I
doe moſt gladly knowe &amp; allowe: ſo that there
neded not in any thinge oure aduyſe herein, yf
we had not bene inſtantly requeſted there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
by certayne brethren, whoſe earneſt &amp; godly
deſyre, we would not, nor durſt not refuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4739:64"/>
The LORDE haue mercye vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and ſhortely breake Sathans head, and throw
downe all power, that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ryueth to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre
the trewe and pure ſeruyce of
GOD. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>☞ ¶i. Corinthi. vi. ☞</bibl>
                  <p>¶Set your ſelues at large, &amp; beare not ye the
yoke with the vnbeleuers. For what felowſhip
hath righteouſneſſe with vnrighteouſneſſe? or
what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani hath light with darknes? or what
concorde hath Chriſt with Belial? ether what
part hath he that beleueth with an infydel? or
how agreeth the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God with Idolles?
For ye are the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the liuing God (as ſaid
God: I will dwell amongeſt them, &amp; walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt
them: &amp; wilbe theyr God, &amp; they ſhall
be my people: wherfore come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſeperate your ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them (ſayth the
Lord:) &amp; touche no vncleane thinge, ſo wyll I
receyue you, &amp; wyll be a father vnto you: &amp; ye
ſhalbe my ſonnes and doughters, ſayth the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
Lorde.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>¶Iob. xx.</bibl>
                  <p>¶Knoweſt thou not this, namely, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the beginninge (euer ſince the creacion of man
vpon the earth) the gladneſſe of the vngodlye
hath bene ſhorte, and that the ioye of ypo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
crites, continued but the twinkeling
of an eye?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
